<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnbeliefe of St. Thomas the Apostle laid open for the comfort of all that desire to belieue. Whereunto is added a comfortable treatise for all that are afflicted in soule or body. The first armeth vs against despaire in the houre of death; the second against impatience vnder the crosse. By Nicholas Bound, Doctor in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Bownd, Nicholas, d. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849119</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14254</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14254)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 779:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnbeliefe of St. Thomas the Apostle laid open for the comfort of all that desire to belieue. Whereunto is added a comfortable treatise for all that are afflicted in soule or body. The first armeth vs against despaire in the houre of death; the second against impatience vnder the crosse. By Nicholas Bound, Doctor in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Bownd, Nicholas, d. 1613.</author>
                  <author>Bownd, Nicholas, d. 1613. Treatise ful of consolation. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 201, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Legat] for Robert Allot at the blacke Beare in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue, with cancel general title page, of Bownd, Nicholas.  The unbeleefe of S. Thomas the apostle (STC 3441.5). In two parts. Includes Bownd, Nicholas.  A Treatise ful of consolation.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The vnbeleefe of S. Thomas.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; print show through. Lacks part 2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Patience --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14254:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14254:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The vnbeliefe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle, laid open for the comfort <hi>of all that deſire to beleeue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added a comfortable Treatiſe for all that are afflicted in ſoule or body.</p>
            <p>The firſt armeth vs againſt deſpaire in the houre of death; the ſecond againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience vnder the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nicholas Bound,</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Allott</hi> at the blacke Beare in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14254:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14254:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>ROBERT GARDENER Knight, and</hi> to the vertuous Ladie <hi>ANNE GAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DENER his religious and louing</hi> wife, their owne hearts deſire <hi>in Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>RIght Worſhipfull Sir, though the kingdome of Ireland did bereaue his countrey of yours, of a great part of that good, which by a certain right it hoped for from you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by reaſon of your long ſeruice there vnder Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> of bleſſed memorie, in the chiefeſt and moſt honourable ſeate of Iuſtice, by the ſpace of <hi>15.</hi> or <hi>16.</hi> yeares together: yet the benefite vnto both the Kingdomes was thought to be ſo great thereby, that the loſſe was ſo much the more eaſily borne.</p>
            <p>And now at the laſt this countrey doth willingly acknowledge, that it hath great
<pb facs="tcp:14254:3"/> cauſe to thanke God, not onely for your ſafe returne vnto it ſome years paſt, furniſhed with greater experience for gouernment; but alſo with hope of neuer departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them any more: ſauing that in your last imployment, vnder his Highnes (whome God long preſerue) into his Ilands of <hi>Iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> and <hi>Garneſie,</hi> they were ſuſpended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hope by the ſpace of certaine moneths.</p>
            <p>Which beeing faithfully performed and ended, their hope is renued, that you bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now at the laſt, <hi>merito tuo maximo donatus rude,</hi> may ſay of this countrey <hi>Here is my reſt.</hi> Which my ſelfe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more ſpeciall cauſe to deſire in regard my miniſterie, which by your preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you haue often and long giuen great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance vnto.</p>
            <p>And you, good Madame, both ſince th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> happie ioyning of you both together, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> long before, by your continuall comming to the publike aſſemblies, though a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way off; both winter and ſommer; neue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hindered by the heate of the one, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14254:3"/> cold of the other, and that by the ſpace of <hi>20.</hi> yeares, haue giuen ſo good an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, like vnto thoſe, that traueled without weariſomnes <hi>through the vaile of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> with hope to <hi>appeare before God in Syon;</hi> that you haue incouraged many vnto the like paines, and haue left the ſlothfull without excuſe. By which, &amp; ſome other good examples like this, the credit of Gods word among vs hath in ſome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſort beene hetherto vpheld.</p>
            <p>For which, and for many other great fauours from you both, I preſent theſe ſmall fruits of my poore labours vnto you, as a perpetuall teſtimonie of my thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes vnto you; and to God for you. Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to multiplie his graces vpon you, and long to preſerue you to your owne mutuall comfort, and the good of ſo many, as doe depend vpon you.</p>
            <p>And the like bleſsing of God be vpon the good and forward hopes of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull <hi>M. William Spring</hi> your onely child; that his youth may be ſtill ſo ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:14254:4"/> with religion and learning, that in time to come he may in the ſeate of Iuſtice for the good of his countrey, by his deſerts goe beyond all his progenitors: and ſo long vphold the credit of that right worſhipfull houſe. And ſo I moſt humbly take my leaue of you all. <hi>Norton in Suff. Iun. 24. 1608.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all reuerend and dutifull affection,</hi> Nicolas Bownde.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14254:4"/>
            <head>THE VNBELEEFE OF. S. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle laid open, for the <hi>comfort of all that deſire to beleeue:</hi> which armeth vs againſt <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire in the houre</hi> of death.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 20.24. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But Thomas one of the twelue, called Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dymus, was not with them, when Ieſus came. <bibl>
                        <hi>25</hi>
                     </bibl> The other Diſciples therefore ſaid vnto him, We haue ſeene the Lord: but he ſaid vnto them, Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nayles, and put my finger into the print of the nayles, and put mine hand into his ſide, I will not beleeue it. <bibl>
                        <hi>26</hi>
                     </bibl> And eight daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter again his Diſciples were within, and Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas with them. Then came Ieſus, when the doores were ſhut, and ſtood in the middes, and ſaid; Peace be vnto you. <bibl>
                        <hi>27</hi>
                     </bibl> After he ſaid to Thomas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Put thy finger here, and ſee mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands, and put forth thine hand, and put it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>to my ſide: and be not faithleſſe, but faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14254:5"/>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>28</hi>
                     </bibl> Then Thomas anſwered, and ſaide vnto him, My Lord, and my God. <bibl>
                        <hi>29</hi>
                     </bibl> Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaide vnto him, Thomas, becauſe thou has<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeene me, thou beleeueſt: bleſſed are they, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> haue not ſeene, and haue beleeued.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture is appointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be read for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goſpel vpon S. <hi>Thomas</hi> day, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tainet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a memorable ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of him, whoſe bleſſed memori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we keepe vpon that day: to that end that we might be thankful vnto Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for him, and for the excellent gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſtowed vpon him, and the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> good done to the Church by his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſterie and preaching: and that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> might labour to imitate his vertue and to profit by his great infirmitie wherein conſiſteth the true and rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> obſeruation of this, and all other ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> like daies.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14254:5"/>
            <p>And not in the worſhipping of him, and praying to him, and ſetting vp candles before his image, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to him, as they did in the time of Poperie; when they praied vnto God to be heard at his interceſſion, and for his merits, and blood ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; as they did vpon other ſuch daies for the reſt of the Apoſtles, and Saints. And they thought that the celebrating of thoſe daies was a great honour and ſeruice acceptable vnto them, and they kept them to that ende, that they might become their patrons, and fare the better for their ſakes before God: and they know no other vſe of them vnto this day.</p>
            <p>Wherein they offer great indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto Chriſt, firſt, in robbing and ſpoyling him of the honour and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his mediation and interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to whom onely it belongeth: of whom the Apoſtle thus writeth: it is Chriſt which is dead, yea or rather
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14254:6"/> which is riſen againe:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 8.24.</note> who is alſo at the right hand of God, &amp; maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt alſo for vs, and therefore who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? And Chriſt himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thus ſpeaketh of his owne office: Whatſoeuer ye ask in my name,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14 13.</note> that wil I doe, that the father may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in the ſonne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they doe great wrong vnto him, in hallowing any daies to the honour of any, but of God alone. For all things that are ſanctified, are ſanctified to his honour and worſhip onely, who only is to be worſhipped &amp; ſerued with diuine worſhip: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the bread and wine in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper, and the water in Baptiſme, are ſanctified to the honour of Chriſt, and of none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: as thoſe that repreſent vnto v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the breaking of his bodie, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhedding of his moſt pretious bloo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the forgiuenes of our ſinnes. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14254:6"/> ſo are and ought the Churches to be confecrated to the name and honour of God alone (who onely is there to be ſerued) and not of any Saint, as in time paſt they haue beene.</p>
            <p>And ſo ought the daies alſo: As vnder the law all the Sabbaths were conſecrated vnto the honour of God the creator of heauen and earth: and vnder the Goſpel vnto the honour of Chriſt the Redeemer of his Church: and all other daies, that are now put a part among vs from the common affaires of the world, they are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that ende, that God might be honoured in them, and by them.</p>
            <p>And therefore we put a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene theſe holy daies, and the Sabbath, or Lords day. Firſt of all in that we know this later to ſtand vpon a better foundation then they, as hauing his inſtitution from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſo doth binde all nations, and is perpetuall,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14254:7"/> neuer to be changed. Whereas the former haue their warrant only from men, and ſo doe not binde all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches alike, and may be changed, yea taken cleane away: and ſerue onely for Chriſtian policie, and good order in the Church, that men vpon theſe daies might come together, and ſerue God. And therefore it is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, that there ſhould not be too many of them, leaſt thereby men ſhould be hindred from the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie workes of their callings; which hath mooued the reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, as in this Realme, ſo elſ-where, to cut off many that were vſed in the time of Poperie, and ſo to keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in a mediocritie, neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing too many, nor putting downe all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, in the manner of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the one, and the other: for on the Chriſtian Sabbath the lawes of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14254:7"/> our kingdome and Church doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine all men from many things, as from markets, and faires, and keeping of Aſſiſes and Seſſions for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice: which they doe tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and permit vpon other holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies. Whereas in the time of blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe they ſometimes preferred theſe daies before the Sabbath; and had more ſolemne ſeruice and feaſts vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and counted it a more dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne then to worke, then vpon the Sabbath day.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, they appointing theſe daies to the honor of men, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by greatly diſhonour the Saints the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For what greater diſhonour can there be vnto any man, then to make him a traytor? and to giue vnto him that honour, that is due onely to the Prince? And if any ſhould in ſimplicitie and good will aſcribe ſo much to the greateſt noble man in the Realme, that at the laſt he ſhould
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14254:8"/> giue him the titles that belong vnto the King, and ſo bring him into the ſuſpicion of treaſon againſt his will, it were no honour, but diſhonour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: So the Papiſts in extolling the Saints ſo highly, that they conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate daies vnto them, and thereby ſeeke to honour them, and hope that therefore they will become Patrons vnto them: all which are proper vnto Chriſt; in ſo doing they diſhonour them: for they make them, as much as lieth in them, to be traytors vnto Chriſt, in robbing him of that honor that is proper vnto him.</p>
            <p>And theſe Saints if they were now aliue vpon earth, would not onely not take this honor vnto themſelues, and thanke them for it, but altogether refuſe it, and rebuke them for it: as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at Lyſtra, when they brought buls with garlands, and would haue ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed vnto them: They rent their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14254:8"/> cloathes, and ranne in among them,<note place="margin">Act. 14 14</note> ſaying, O men, why doe you theſe things? we are men ſubiect vnto the like paſſions, that you be: and preach vnto you, that you ſhould turne from theſe vaine things vnto the liuing God.</p>
            <p>IN this text there are theſe foure things principally to be obſerued: firſt of all the great infidelitie of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle, who did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the reſurrection of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported vnto him by all his fellow A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who had ſeene him, v. 24, 25. Secondly, the great mercie of Chriſt, who did not caſt him off, and leaue him to periſh in this vnbeleefe of his, but moſt louingly in time conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſought to pull him out of it by all good meanes; euen the very ſame, which himſelfe deſired. verſ. 26, 27. Thirdly, the increaſe of faith in <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> by theſe meanes, appearing by the confeſſion that he made, after that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14254:9"/> he was thus confirmed, namely, that he did beleeue, not onely that he was riſen againe, but for him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calleth him, his Lord, and his God. v. 28. Laſtly, here Chriſt vpon this occaſion deliuereth a generall doctrine, and ſo applieth this fact of <hi>Thomas</hi> vnto the whole church; euen that they ſhould be bleſſed, who ſhould beleeue in him, though they did not ſee him, as he had done.</p>
            <p>I doe not purpoſe to intreat of all theſe, but onely of ſo much, as doth concerne the vnbeleefe of S. <hi>Thomas.</hi> But before I come to it, it may ſeeme ſomewhat ſtrange, that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Goſpel doth write this of his fellow Apoſtle, ſeeing it tendeth ſo wholly to his diſcredit. The other Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts all of them haue left it out, it may ſeeme in fauour of him; and it might be thought, that it had beene better, if he had paſſed it ouer with ſilence alſo. But this Apoſtle liuing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14254:9"/> longer then all the reſt, about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after Chriſt, and ſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their writings, doth adde this, as a matter of ſpeciall moment: as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede in it there is offered to the Church great inſtruction and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>And this plaine dealing of his is a note of that integritie, that is to be found in all the Scriptures, as beeing penned by the ſpirit of God. For they came not in old time, as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.2.</note> by the will of man: but holy men of God did ſpeake and write, as they were mooued by the holy Ghoſt. And therefore they greatly differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the writings of men, which ſauour of the ſpirit of men; and ſo are in many things partiall: as this is a common fault in many Hiſtoriographers, that they flatter great men, and ſpeak one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their vertues, which they ſet out to the full: but their vices either they wholly conceale, or lightly paſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14254:10"/> ouer; eſpecially when they are their friends, and of the ſame ranke and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with them, as S. <hi>Thomas</hi> was vnto the Apoſtle S. <hi>Iohn.</hi> But it is not ſo in the Scriptures, which proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpirit of truth, are no more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, then God himſelfe, with whome there is no reſpect of perſons:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 2.11.</note> in ſo much that the penners of them doe lay open the greateſt ſinnes of the greateſt men in their time, euen of the Kings and of the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sam. 2.8.</note>As of <hi>Heli,</hi> how he honoured his children aboue God, and cauſed the ſacrifices of the Lord to be deſpiſed, and troaden vnder foote: and of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> king of Iudah, how he cauſed his ſonnes to paſſe through the fire in the valley of Ben-hinnom,<note place="margin">Chr. 33.6</note> and gaue himſelfe to witchcraft, and to char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and to ſorcerie: and vſed them that had familiar ſpirits, and ſoothſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and did very much euill in the ſight of the Lord, to anger him: yea,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14254:10"/> the Prophets do not ſpare them, that were neareſt in blood to them, or neareſt in any bond of affinitie, or friendſhip.<note place="margin">Num 12.</note> For <hi>Moſes</hi> doth ſet out the murmuring of <hi>Aaron</hi> his owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall brother, and of his ſiſter <hi>Miriam,</hi> and how God did puniſh them for it: which he did not to de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame them, or with a minde to be reuenged of them: for the Lord gaue this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of him, that he was a very meeke man,<note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> aboue all the men that were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtles doe write the truth boldly and ſincerely of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Apoſtles, though their faults were exceeding great, and not the like almoſt heard of.<note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> As how <hi>Iudas</hi> did for thirtie pieces of ſiluer ſell and betray his Lord and maſter Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of his moſt deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And how <hi>Peter</hi> did not onely denie him once, but the ſecond time did forſweare him,<note place="margin">verſ. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yea did curſe and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14254:11"/> banne himſelfe, if that euer he did but know him.</p>
            <p>And to conclude this point, their vprightnes in their writings appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſo much the more, that they doe not ſpare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, but publiſh their owne faults to the praiſe of God, as his ſpirit in them did direct them. For <hi>Moſes</hi> declareth at large how ſlow &amp; backward he was to take vpon him that calling, that God had appointed him vnto, and what excuſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies he made, in ſo much that the Lord was very angrie with him.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xod. 4.14</note>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Dauid</hi> writeth of the adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and murder, that he had ſecretly committed againſt Bath-ſheba, and her husband Vriah: and confeſſeth openly, that he had deſerued death for both of them, when he thus pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 51.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iddamim.</note> Deliuer me from bloods, O Lord. So likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpareth not himſelfe, becauſe it was not he, but the ſpirit of God that ſpake in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14254:11"/> him,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.13</note> in that he had perſecuted the Church of God cruelly, and waſted it. This kind of ſimple dealing is one argument not of the leaſt moment, among many other, to euince that the Scriptures are written by Gods ſpirit: and are therefore Canonicall, for they are not partiall: but the ſpirit of truth &amp; ſimple dealing doth mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly appeare euery where in them.</p>
            <p>But it may further be demanded, though ſuch things as theſe be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Saints, whether they ſhould be read openly in the Church vpon thoſe holy daies, that cary their name: as if, when we keepe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of a man, all his euill deedes ſhould be reckoned vp, tending to his infamie and diſcredit. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which, as the prouidence of God therein is to be acknowledged, who hath thus diſpoſed of it: ſo we are to reuerence and highly eſteeme
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14254:12"/> the godly wiſdome of thoſe holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who did firſt appoint thoſe daies thus to be kept. For they did it to the honour of God; and therefore would by the reading of theſe texts of ſcripture haue all men know, what the Saints were of themſelues: and what infirmities, vnbeleefe, and other ſinnes they were ſubiect vnto; euen the ſame that we are: as Paul and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas ſaide of themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 14.14.</note> We are men ſubiect to the like paſſions, that you are: and as S. Iames ſaith of the Prophet Elias,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 5.17.</note> that he was a man ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the like paſſions, as we are. That ſo if they were any thing, we might know from whence it came, and ſo as Paul ſaith of himſelfe, I am the leaſt of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> which am not worthie to be called an Apoſtle, becauſe I perſecuted the Church of God: but by the grace of God, I am that I am: and his grace which is in me, was not in vaine: but I labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14254:12"/> more aboundantly then they all; yet not I, but the grace of God which is with me. So we might ſay of them, beeing put in minde by the Scriptures that are read euen vpon thoſe daies, wherein we keepe the greateſt memorie of them, what they were of themſelues, and what they were by the grace of God: and ſo not ſo much honour them, as praiſe God for them.</p>
            <p>For the purpoſe of thoſe ancient fathers of the Church, who apointed theſe daies thus to be kept, was not to ſet out the Saints themſelues, that we might glory in them, and in their merits: but in the merits of Chriſt, &amp; in the mercie of God ſhewed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his ſake: and ſo not only to teach vs how rightly to eſteem of them, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat in them, as in a glaſſe we might ſee, what we are ſubiect vnto: and yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow gratious God is to pore ſinners, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo might take comfort in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14254:13"/> of God ſhewed to them. As here what great vnbeeleefe was in Saint Thomas, and yet Chriſt did help him of it, and ſaued him? to ſhew vs, that we are as full of vnbeleefe, as he, and much more: yet Chriſt will not refuſe vs, if we do not obſtinatly remaine in it, but are willing to be holpen of it, and haue a deſire to beleeue, by the meanes that he ſhall beſtow vpon vs. And this is the vſe that we are to mak of the vnbeleefe of S. Thomas, euen then when we heare it read vpon his day.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts did not ſo: for beſides that they had a great number of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Saints in their Cale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, whoſe names were not written in the booke of life; ſome of them traytors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as ill, or worſe then they: vpon their feſtiuall daies, they cauſed to be read out of <hi>Legenda aurea,</hi> that is their Legend of lies, a ſtorie of their liues, full of all vertues, and miracles that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14254:13"/> they wrought, ſome in their life, ſome after their death, whereof moſt were fained, and ſome of them moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. And thus they made them to be Gods vpon the earth, not making mention of any fault of theirs at any time, eſpecially ſo great as theſe, that we haue heard of in S. Thomas, S. Paul, and the reſt.</p>
            <p>Whereby it came to paſſe, partly by the obſeruation of thoſe daies, and partly by hearing what was then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of them out of their ſtories, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people were brought into a ſuperſtitious admiration of them, and had no hope by imitating their vertues to be like them: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did worſhip them by meanes of the ſtraunge and incredible things, that they heard of them. And ſo here was no comfort from them for poore ſinners, but only for their merits and mediation: for they did not ſpeake of their infirmities and falls. But we ſee,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14254:14"/> how the Scriptures ſet out the true Saints of God after an other manner: not onely in their miracles and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but in their greateſt corruptions and ſinnes: that we knowing what they were of themſelues, and what they are by the mercie of God, and the grace of Chriſt; the pooreſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner might be comforted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by the one, and giue thanks to God for the other. Seeing that there is no ſinne in themſelues, which they haue not ſeene pardoned and cured in ſome of the Saints or other: nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grace wanting to themſelues, which by that experience of Gods goodnes which they haue ſcene in others, they might not hope for in themſelues in ſome meaſure.</p>
            <p>BVt I come to the principal thing in this text, which is the great infirmitie, and wonderfull vnbeleefe that was in the Apoſtle <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in theſe wordes of his owne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14254:14"/> that when the reſt of the Diſciples had told him, that they had ſeene the Lord, he anſwered them, Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nayles, and put my finger into the print of the nailes, and put mine hand into his ſide, I will not beleeue it.</p>
            <p>The circumſtance of time, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occurrants going before this, doe aggrauate the greatnes of his vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. For this was done the eight day after Chriſts reſurrection: then he did ſhew himſelfe vnto <hi>Thomas,</hi> as it is ſaide, verſ. 26. Eight daies after his Diſciples were againe within, and Thomas with them, then came Ieſus, when the doores were ſhut, &amp; ſtood in the middes, and ſaid, Peace be vnto you: after he ſaid to Thomas, Put thy finger here, and ſee mine hands: and put forth thine hand, and put it into my ſide, and be not faithleſſe, but faithfull. In the meane ſeaſon he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeared vnto <hi>Marie Magdalene</hi> at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14254:15"/> the ſepulchre the firſt day of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection earely in the morning, and ſhee knew him: for he called her <hi>Marie,</hi> and ſhee anſwered, <hi>Rabboni,</hi> that is to ſay, maſter, verſ. 17. at what time, ſhee was willed to goe tell the Diſciples, that he was riſen: and ſhee did ſo: and alſo ſhewed them, what other words he had ſpoken vnto her: but none of them did beleeue her: as <hi>S. Marke</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Mark. 16.11.</note> Thus at the firſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, Thomas was incredulous, as well as the reſt. And the ſame day toward the euening he appeared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two other as they were in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Emaus, and they returned preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and tould the Diſciples of it, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they did not beleeue them neither.<note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame night therefore he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto the eleuen, as they ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> together, and caſt in their teeth the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vnbeleefe, and hardnes of heart, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they beleeued not them, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had now twiſe told them, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14254:15"/> had ſeene him, beeing riſen againe, verſ. 14. And becauſe their vnbeleefe was ſo great at that time, to put them out of al doubt for the time to come, he ſhewed them his hands, and his ſide that was pierced, and the print of the nayles in the one, &amp; of the ſpeare in the other, and bad them looke on them, that they might know that it was he indeede,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.20.</note> as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt doth report it.</p>
            <p>At this time <hi>Thomas</hi> was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent among them. The Lord of his infinite wiſdome and goodnes thus diſpoſing of it, for the further good both of Thomas, and of all the reſt, and of the whole Church: that by this meanes there might be a new confirmation of his reſurrection, by a ſecond and more ſenſible appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: when they ſhould not onely ſee againe the print of the nailes in his hands, but for Thomas alſo to put his finger into them. But in the meane
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14254:16"/> while, all the reſt tell him, what they had ſeene, namely, not onely Chriſt in ſome forme, but ſo certenly that he ſpake vnto them, and ſhewed them his hands and his feete, and the print of the nayles in them, ſo that they could not poſſibly be deceiued in ſo cleare a matter: yet for all this he not onely not giueth credit vnto ſome one of them ſeuerally, but not vnto all of them ioyntly, beeing ſo many, and ſo credible witneſſes: and further, is ſo wilfull and obſtinate, and ſo addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to his owne ſenſes and feeling, that he tells them plainly, that vnles he himſelfe ſee the print of the nayles in his hands, and may put his finger into them; and the print of the ſpeare in his ſide, and may put his hand into that, he will neuer beleeue it.</p>
            <p>This is a maruelous thing, &amp; may ſeeme iuſtly to be wondred at, that he beeing an Apoſtle, and one that had beene conuerſant with our Sauiour
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14254:16"/> Chriſt a long time, and had heard his doctrine, and ſeene his miracles; yea, had preached ſaluation in his name with the reſt: and had heard Chriſt ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay, that he muſt be put to death, and the third day riſe againe: that though he did generally beleeue in him, yet he was not perſwaded parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of this article of his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But ſuch is our corruption, and we doe ſo receiue the Spirit but in meaſure, that we may be true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in many particulars: as we ſee in the Apoſtle here, who beleeuing Chriſt to be the ſonne of God, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the world, and ſo held the maine point of ſaluation, failed in the particular manner, and was not yet perſwaded of the truth of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. But for all this we are not to account him, as an infidell, but thinke thus with our ſelues, if ſuch a man as he, was ſubiect vnto ſo great doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14254:17"/> no maruell then, if I in many particulars finde my faith to be ſo full of doubting and wauering. Onely let vs in theſe doubtings ſtill vſe the meanes, and God will at one time or other bleſſe ſome of them vnto vs. As Thomas here not beleeuing that Chriſt was riſen, though the reſt of the Apoſtles did tell him of it, did not forſake their companie, but came into their aſſemblies vpon the Lords day, to ſerue Chriſt with them, and then Chriſt did appeare vnto him, and ridde him of his vnbeleefe. Whereas if he had beene ſtill abſent, as he was before, and therefore hee remained longer in his vnbeleefe then they, God might haue depriued him of all meanes, and iuſtly haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him vp to his vnbeleefe.</p>
            <p>But this is a greater wonder, and herein his vnbeleefe doth appeare much more: that beſides the former things, when the other Apoſtles,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14254:17"/> whom he by long experience knew to be very reuerend and credible me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, told him that they had ſeene the Lord, and after what manner, euen with the prints of the nailes, &amp; of the ſpeare in his body, yet he ſo diſtruſted all of them, that he would beleeue none of them. Oftentimes wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue meaner men and of leſſe credite in matters of great vncertentie, and of ſmall moment: therefore not to beleeue ſo many and of ſo good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and in a thing of great moment, it beeing true alſo, doth plainly ſhew, how deeply vnbeleefe was rooted in him. Eſpecially if we conſider how he further addeth, that if there were neuer ſo many more of them, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, what they will be, that ſhould tell him ſo, he would beleeue none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but his owne ſelfe, and his owne ſenſe and feeling: for v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les he could ſee in his hands the print of the nailes, and put his finger into the print of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14254:18"/> nailes, and put his hand into his ſide, he would not beleeue it.</p>
            <p>And it ſeemeth, that the reſt of the Apoſtles were ſubiect vnto this vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, though not in the like meaſure: for when Marie Magdalen at Chriſts commandement, came vnto them, and finding them weeping &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, tolde them for their comfort, that Chriſt was riſen; though they heard her ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar. 16.11</note> that he was aliue, and had appeared to her, they beleeued it not: nay they were ſo farre from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing it, that her wordes ſeemed vnto them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uk. 24.11.</note> as a fained thing: ſo that they were not only ſomwhat doutfull of the matter, but did wholly reiect it as a meere fable. Moreouer, when two of the diſciples, the name of the one beeing Cleopas, going to Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus, Chriſt did appeare vnto them in the way, and though they knew him not at the firſt, yet at the laſt their eyes were opened, ſo that they knew
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14254:18"/> him perfectly, and ſo returning to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, ſaide vnto the eleuen, The Lord is riſen indeede: and ſo doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch it conſtantly with a note of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance; and told them alſo, what was done in the way, and how they knew him at the laſt:<note place="margin">Mar. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> They beleeued them neither. So that this caſe was not of Thomas alone, but of all the reſt, that we might ſee that the beſt ſeruants of God of all, are greatly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered with theſe remnants of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. That as Dauid ſaith, If thou,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> O Lord, ſtraitly markeſt iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand? that is, not the beſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, much leſſe ſuch a wretch as I: So we may ſay, if theſe holy men were ſo full of vnbeleefe in this thing, no maruell, if ſuch a poore ſinner as I am, ſtand doubtfull and perplexed in many things: and as Chriſt did ſuccour them, I hope he will be mercifull vnto me, that deſire to beleeue.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14254:19"/>
            <p>And it is very probable, that the reſt of the Apoſtles in this vnbeleefe of theirs, were ſubiect vnto the ſame temptations that Thomas was, and had the ſame thoughts to hinder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from beleeuing, that he had: and namely, that they ſpake within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as he did openly, though for ſhame they did not vtter it, as often it falleth out, that many are afraid to vtter their temptations, they are ſo fearefull and ſo ſtraunge, that they thinke, that none are poſſeſſed with them, but themſelues. But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle telleth the Corinthians, that no tentation had taken hold of them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 10.13.</note> but ſuch as appertaineth vnto man; that is, which proceedeth of mans infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and which mans nature is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto: that they might not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, or diſpaire for that, that he had ſaid vnto them. And therefore he addeth, that God is faithfull, and would not ſuffer them to be tempted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14254:19"/> aboue that, that they were able, but would giue an iſſue with the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they might be able to beare it: as he did here vnto the reſt of the Apoſtles, and to Thomas himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And that they had indeede the ſame thoughts of vnbeleef that Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas had, it appeareth by the fact of Chriſt. For when he came among them, and they were abaſhed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.3</note> ſuppoſing that they had ſeene a ſpirit, he ſaid vnto them; Why are ye troubled? and wherfore do thoughts ariſe in your hearts? Behold mine hands, and my feete, for it is my ſelfe; handle me, and ſee: and when he had thus ſpoken he ſhewed them his hands and his feete. So that Chriſt in ſhewing them his hands and feete, that ſo they might be ridde of thoſe thoughts and doubts, that hindred them from beleeuing; did manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, that he knew the thoughts of their hearts to be theſe, that vnleſſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14254:20"/> they ſaw in his hands and feete the print of the nayles, they would not beleeue that it was he. Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like a skilfull phyſitian of their ſoules did applie his medicine accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their maladie; and therefore when as at his firſt apparition he did ſhew vnto them his hands and his feete, he doing all things in wiſdom and to ſome good purpoſe, did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declare, what thoughts of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe they were troubled with.</p>
            <p>If ſuch holy men as theſe, who had ſo many meanes to helpe their faith, did not ſufficiently profit by them at the firſt; but were found thus incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous: then we may be aſſured, that vnbeleefe is more deepely rooted in vs, then we be a ware of: and if after many meanes, and long continuance in the ſame we finde it in our ſelues more then we would, we muſt not too much ſuſpect our ſelues, as long as we are ſorie for it, and doe groane
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14254:20"/> vnder it, as vnder an heauie burden, deſiring to be eaſed of the ſame. For indeed there is no ſinne in the world, that hath more infected mankinde, then that: it came in with our firſt parents euen in Paradiſe, and it will continue as long as there is any man vpon earth: it is the firſt ſinne that poſſeſſeth all men: and it is the laſt that we muſt ſtriue againſt: in ſo much that when we haue ouercome all other, then wil our vnbeleefe moſt of all trouble vs. And eſpecially we ſhall finde this to be true in all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and in the houre of death: when the temptations of pride, of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uptuouſnes, of reuenge, &amp;c. ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaue vs, as hauing receiued their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eadly blow; then will vnbeleefe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtruſt fall vpon vs afreſh, as though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had neuer beene wounded, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſo much as incountred with.</p>
            <p>For ſeeing that faith is, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſtle calleth it,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.16.</note> A ſheild wherewith
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14254:21"/> we may quench all the fierie darts of the deuill: therefore he laboureth moſt of all to pull it out of our hands altogether, or ſo to weaken it in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, that his darts may eaſily pearce through it into our ſoules to deſtroy them: that is, his temptation may deceiue vs one way or other. For as long as this ſheild of faith is whol, and we be able to hold it out againſt our ſpirituall enemie, we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt him, whether he temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs vnto any ſinne in time to come, or for any ſinne of the time paſt. But if we let fall the ſheild of faith, or doe not defend our ſelues with it; we lie open to all temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan: that is, if we altogethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> giue ouer faith, or fall to doubting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the truth of his word.</p>
            <p>Adam and Eue were firſt ouer come by vnbeleefe, and that was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe of their ruine: for the deuill b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſputing with the woman like a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14254:21"/> Sophiſter, brought her at the laſt to cal into queſtion the truth of Gods word, and to ſay,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.3.</note> Of the fruit of the tree, which is in the middes of the garden, God hath ſaid, ye ſhall not eate of it, neither ſhall ye touch it, leaſt ye die: whereas the Lord had ſaid in expreſſe words before,<note place="margin">chap. 2 17.</note> In the day, that ye ſhall eate thereof, ye ſhall die the death: that is, ye ſhall aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die: which if they had ſteadfaſtly beleeued, they had not beene ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his temptation. So in all ſinne that we commit there is vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, more or leſſe; for if we fall by preſumption, then we beleeue not his threatnings; if by deſpaire, then we beleeue not his promiſes. And iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith though it principally loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the promiſes of ſaluation; yet generally it reſpecteth the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord of God. The manifold ſinnes then that we ſee in other, and doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommit our ſelues, doe apparently
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14254:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14254:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14254:23"/> ſhew, how full of vnbeleefe we and the whole world is: for if we did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue God to be true in his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and in his promiſes, we ſhould be kept from ſinne.</p>
            <p>Beſides, when men are fallen into any ſinnes, what is the cauſe that they doe not ſpeedily repent them of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo leaue them, but onely vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe? For if they did rightly beleeue either the promiſes of God, as, At what time ſoeuer a ſinner ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from his ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zek. 18.21.</note> and doe that which is lawfull and right, he ſhall ſurely liue, and ſhall not die: all his tranſgreſſions, that he hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall not be remembred, or laide to his charge: they would preſently repent, and leaue their ſinnes, that they might be forgiuen them. Or if they beleeued his threatnings; as, Kiſſe the ſonne,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note> leaſt he be angrie, and ye periſh in the midde way, when his wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th ſhall ſuddenly burne, bleſſed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14254:23"/> are all that truſt in him: they would ſpeedily repent, whiles mercie is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; leaſt God take them away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or bring ſome great iudgement vpon them. But contrarie to the truth of Gods word (according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of vnb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leefe) they imagine ſome thing of their owne head, wherein they reſt; and let all men ſay to the contrarie, what they will, they will beleeue none but themſelues, &amp; their owne conceit.</p>
            <p>As that, they ſhall doe wel enough though they continue in their ſinnes: or that they ſhall haue time enough hereafter to repent them at their lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: and that they may repent them when they liſt, or ſome ſuch like: of which there is nothing promiſed in the word of God, but the cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſet down often and very plainly. Therefore that men, when they haue fallen into any ſinne, do ſo eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in them, and either repent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14254:24"/> not at all, or doe it very ſlowly, &amp; that doth bewray ſufficiently, how full of vnbeleefe they are. Seeing therefore that it is ſo vniuerſally ſpread ouer all men, no maruell, if the better ſort doe complaine ſo much of it in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and finde it to be a great deale more, then they would.</p>
            <p>Agine, let vs be in trouble, &amp; want meanes to helpe our ſelues, and ſee if we be not prone to diſtruſt God? and ſo not to depend on his prouidence: but rather to vſe vnlawfull meanes to helpe our ſelues: or to be too reſtles &amp; vnquiet in the vſe of thoſe that are lawfull: and ſo either altogether to forget to ſeeke vnto God by prayer: or elſe to doe it very coldly, and with little hope. Though God hath ſaide, Call vpon me in thy trouble,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 50.15.</note> ſo will I deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebr. 13.6.</note> And be contented with thoſe things, that ye haue, for God hath ſaid, I will not faile thee, nor forſake
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14254:24"/> thee.<note place="margin">Heb. 6.31.</note> And firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God; and his righteouſneſſe, and all things neceſſary ſhall be miniſtred vnto you: and a thouſand ſuch promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more: which doth ſhew that vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe poſſeſſeth men euery manner of way, and there is no man in the world altogether free from it, though it be a great deale more in ſome, then in other.</p>
            <p>And to be ſhort, when we are te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto any ſinne, we by lamentable experience finde, that we are too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ouercome, becauſe we beleeue not Gods threatnings, that he will aſſuredly puniſh it. And when we are tempted for any ſinne, how ſoone are we readie to deſpaire, becauſe we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not the promiſes of forgiuenes vnto the repentant? So that this ſinne is found in the whole courſe of our life: in ſo much that when we haue ouercome many other ſinnes in the firſt and ſecond table; then we ſhal be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14254:25"/> either wholly ouercome with vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, or greatly polluted with it.</p>
            <p>The Deuill did greatly aſſault our Sauiour Chriſt with this, both in the firſt entrance into his office, and alſo in the laſt diſcharging of it. Firſt of all in the wildernes, when he would by that long time of abſtinence &amp; want of corporall foode by the ſpace of fourtie daies, and fourtie nights, haue perſwaded him, that God had forſaken him, and had no care of him: for then he would haue prouided for him all this while: and therefore he muſt now ſhift for himſelfe, and if he could doe any thing, he muſt ſhew his power, If he be the ſonne of God indeed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 4.3.</note> he muſt command that thoſe ſtones he made bread. Secondly, when he was vpon the croſſe; for then they that paſſed by reuiling him, and wagging their heads,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 27.39.</note> ſaid, If thou be the ſonne of God, come downe from the croſſe: and the Prieſts alſo moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14254:25"/> him, ſaide, He ſaued others, but he cannot ſaue himſelfe: if he be the king of Iſrael, let him now come downe from the croſſe: ſo that they concluded againſt him to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his faith, that God did not care for him, becauſe he did not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently deliuer him.</p>
            <p>Thus by tempting him to vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe in the beginning, he ſought to diſcourage him from it: and by the ſame temptation of vnbeleefe in the ending, to cauſe him to giue it ouer, before he had happily finiſhed it. And after the ſame manner the deuill ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon all the members of Chriſt: in the beginning of their calling, he greatly buffeteth them with vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and puts into them many feares and doubts, that their ſinnes ſhal not be pardoned; that ſo they might as men tired in the combate, giue ouer, and returne to their old byas. And before their death he terrifieth them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14254:26"/> againe with feare, that they ſhall not goe to heauen, that ſo in deſpairing of ſo great a matter, they might giue ouer ſeeking it any longer. But Chriſt did ouercome by the power of his Spirit in thoſe temptations of his, that by the ſame Spirit he might ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour vs in ours.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 2.17.</note> And ſo in all things he was made like his brethren, that he might be mercifull, and a faithfull high Prieſt to make reconciliation for the ſinnes of the people: for in that he ſuffered, and was tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. As he did here in due ſeaſon help the vnbeleefe of the Apoſtles, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto them his hands, and his feet; but moſt of all his weake and poore ſeruant Thomas. For when he had ſaide,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h. 20.25.</note> Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nailes, and put my finger into the print of the nayles, and put my hand into his ſide, I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: Then a little after Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14254:26"/> vnto him, and ſaid vnto him, Put thy finger here,<note place="margin">verſ. 27.</note> and ſee mine hands; and put forth thine hand, and put it into my ſide; and be not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but faithfull.</p>
            <p>BVt to proceede, the firſt degree of Thomas his vnbeleefe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in this, that he did heare this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and of diuers, that were very cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and yet he did not beleeue it: as firſt of all of diuers holy and godly women,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and namely of Marie Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene, and Ioanna, and Marie the mother of Iames, and other women with them, who earely in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning returning from the ſepulchre, told the eleuen that Chriſt was riſen: and alſo he heard it againe of Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas, and an other diſciple,<note place="margin">verſ. 33.</note> who told them, they had ſeene him, and ſpoken with him after his reſurrection: and now the third time he heard it of all his fellow Apoſtles, beeing ten in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, all of them very credible, who did
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14254:27"/> auouch it vnto him vpon their owne knowledge, and ſaide, that they had ſeene him themſelues. It was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the equitie of the law, that in the mouth of two witneſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eut. 19.15</note> or at the mouth of three witneſſes, euery mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould be eſtabliſhed. Therefore there was no colour to diſcredit ſo many witneſſes, eſpecially comming in to teſtifie the ſame truth at ſeuerall times. But herein appeareth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of infidelitie, which is, to cauſe vs, though we heare the truth of God witneſſed vnto vs by ſundrie men, and at diuers times, not to beleeue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of them in diuers things, but onely our ſelues. And though they be neuer ſo graue, and reuerend, and conſtant in auouching of it, &amp; ſound in proouing of it, yet all ſhall be as we thinke, and ſay our ſelues, and not otherwiſe: and thus they are wiſer in their owne conceit,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r. 26.16</note> then ſeauen men that can render a reaſon. Whereby it
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14254:27"/> commeth to paſſe, that they hinder themſelues in their ſaluation: for though God ſend his ſeruants vnto them, to tell them his will, they will beleeue nothing, but as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue themſelues.</p>
            <p>And this though it be a great ſinne, yet it was not proper vnto Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas only, but it was found in the reſt of the Apoſtles at this preſent. And that we might not wonder at it in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without any profit, we ſhall ſee it as deeply rooted in our ſelues, &amp; others: for this is but a looking glaſſe to let vs ſee our owne vnbeleefe in. For how often haue we heard one &amp; the ſame truth conſtantly deliuered vnto vs by the Prophets, Euangeliſts, and Apoſtles? &amp; yet we doe not beleeue them: we haue ſundry times heard them, and read them, yea they haue bin often preached vnto vs, and that by ſundry of the faithfull miniſters and ſeruants of God; and yet we gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14254:28"/> no credit vnto them: and this is too true, whether we looke to Gods fearefull threatnings, or his mercifull promiſes, both for this life, and the life to come.</p>
            <p>How oftentimes, and by how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men haue we heard, that vnleſſe we repent, we ſhall all periſh; and yet very few beleeue it, for they goe on full in their ſinne, and thinke that they ſhall doe well enough. And that euery tree,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 3.10</note> that bringeth not forth good fruit, ſhal be hewen downe, and caſt into the fire: that is, all wicked ones, that will not ſpeedily amend their liues, ſhall be caſt into hell fire: and yet though they liue neuer ſo wickedly, they thinke to be ſaued, as well as the reſt. And though a ſinner doe euill an hundred times,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccles. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and God prolong his daies, yet it ſhall not goe well with him at the laſt; yet men thinke the contrarie, that ſeeing they haue eſcaped in one ſinne vnpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14254:28"/> and the ſecond, &amp; third time, that therefore it ſhall goe well with them for euer: and they thinke, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that becauſe God holds his tongue, he is like them, and liketh their waies well enough.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, how often haue we heard, and by how many, that he that is angrie with his brother vnaduiſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is culpable of iudgement:<note place="margin">Matth. 5.2</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hateth his brother is a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaier: and yet men nouriſh theſe euill affections in themſelues, as though theſe ſayings were vtterly falſe. And hath it not often beene ſounded in our eares by men of great credit, That neither adulterers,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nor fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, ſhall inherit the kingdome of God: but yet I would to God, that the wicked liues of too many did not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly bewray the thoughts of their hearts, namly, that they did not only ſomewhat doubt of the truth of this, but they thinke it to be a meere fable:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14254:29"/> and let men ſay what they wil againſt theſe ſinnes, they will beleeue none but themſelues: ſo wholly are their hearts poſſeſſed with infidelitie.</p>
            <p>Yea let a man come, and deale with one in any ſinne of his, in which he is ſetled, and denounce the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt him out of the truth of his word: and let a ſecond &amp; a third man likewiſe preach the ſame vnto him at an other time: and he yet is reſolute in himſelfe, he knoweth as much of that matter, as any man can tell him, he will beleeue none but his owne deceitfull heart, and his owne feeling; vnleſſe he feele the ſmart of it vpon himſelfe, he will giue no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vnto it: like vnto the men of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who when righteous Lot told them of fire and brimſtone, that ſhould come downe from heauen vpon them for their horrible wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they iudged him to be an old do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foole,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. 19.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and would not beleeue it,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14254:29"/> vntill they ſaw it, and felt it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues burning about their eares, when it was too late.</p>
            <p>By this infidelitie, which is in vs naturally, we are enemies to our own ſaluation, in that we will not beleeue this part of Gods holy word, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto vs often by them, that are worthie of all credit. And this was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he eſtate of all of vs, till God of his great mercie did reforme vs, &amp; purge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of this vnbeleefe, that for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of our liues, and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing vs of our ſinnes, that we might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaued, we would beleeue nothing of Gods iudgements, and of hell fire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough preached by many; but onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch things, as our blind reaſon did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſwade our falſe hearts of: and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e did ſticke faſt vnto, whatſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen ſaid, and of neuer ſo many to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontrarie. And the ſame vnbeleefe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emaineth ſtill in vs in meaſure in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at part, that is vnregenerate.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14254:30"/>
            <p>We muſt therefore examine our ſelues, that we may find it out, &amp; pray to God to helpe vs againſt it, which no doubt he will, if we ſeeke vnto him, and be deſirous to be holpen of it; as he did here his ſeruant Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas the Apoſtle. For this ſtorie of his vnbeleefe is written, to comfort all thoſe that are fallen into vnbeleefe, and are deſirous to be ridde of it, and to beleeue, as this Apoſtle was. But if men for want of due examinatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and triall of their owne heart, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſume of that, that is not in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo imagine that they beleeue when they doe not, or to haue mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith then they haue; they ſhall on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> day finde, that their phantaſie hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deceiued them, and they ſhal be farr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from beeing holpen in that, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> want. For many thinke that it is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſieſt thing in the world to beleeue when as indeede it is the hardeſt; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is more hard to ouercome our re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14254:30"/> in beleeuing, then the affections of our heart in doing: and therefore Chriſt ſaith, The gate is ſtrait,<note place="margin">Math. 7.14.</note> and the way narrow that leadeth vnto life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd few there be that finde it.</p>
            <p>And that which hath bin ſaid of Gods iudgments, it is true alſo of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>romiſes, that there is as much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleefe in vs towards the one, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ards the other. For how often haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e read the ſame ſweet and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able promiſes of God made for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood: yea how often haue they bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reached ouer and ouer againe vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; and yet we rather not beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all, or not as we ſhould. Let vs take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne for example. The Lord ſaith by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> Call vpon me in the day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f thy trouble, ſo I will deliuer thee: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd who ſo euer ſhall call on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame of the Lord ſhall be ſaued.<note place="margin">Ioel 2.22.</note> Yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen trouble and affliction co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h how fewe doe beleeue this to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue? as appeareth by their practiſe;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14254:31"/> for how few or none at all almoſt doe ſeeke vnto the Lord by earneſt and feruent prayer? and they that doe, with how little confidence and hope of beeing heard, doe they practiſe it? which ſheweth howful of vnbeleefe they are.</p>
            <p>Few or none can ſay, as Salomon doth,<note place="margin">Prov. 18.10.</note> that the word of the Lord is their ſtrong tower, and that they run to that, as to their ſure defence: or as Dauid taught the people to ſay, Some truſt in chariots,<note place="margin">Pſal. 20.7.</note> and ſome in horſes, but we remember the name of the Lord our God; that this is the firſt thing that they remember, as that that ſhall doe them moſt good. But prayer is either ſo wholly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or men come to it ſo ſlowly, as it were drawing their legs after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and laſt of all, as though they did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one whit beleeue the promiſes thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> way made vnto them.</p>
            <p>Nay, which is more, if any com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14254:31"/> to them in their trouble, and tell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they haue often found this to be true by experience in themſelues: as Dauid doth, The poore man cried,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.6.</note> and the Lord heard him, and ſaued him out of all his troubles: yet we doe not beleeue that we ſhall finde it to be true in our ſelues. Eſpecially if God deferre vs any while, we can giue no credit to the truth of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, vntill we ſee them verified in our ſelues: but we are readie to ſay, vnleſſe we ſee and feele theſe things in our ſelues, we will not beleeue it.</p>
            <p>Againe, how often, and by how many haue we heard this truth of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> All things worke together for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he beſt vnto them, that loue God: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, God will turne all the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his people vnto their good in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ende: yet when the leaſt croſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth befall vs, how are we diſmaied, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s though this were falſe, becauſe we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe not beleeue it? And if any ſhall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14254:32"/> then ſay vnto vs, be of good comfort, beare it patiently, the Lord herein ſeeketh your good, and you ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> come out of this affliction better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you were before; yet we thinke it a matter impoſſible; yea, a meere fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and that it is better for vs to be otherwiſe, and ſo we will not beleeue him: nor others, though they ſhould come immediately, and tell vs the ſame vpon good trial, that they found it to be ſo in themſelues, as Daui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> It is good for me that I hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beene afflicted, that I may learne thy ſtatutes:<note place="margin">67.</note> and before I was afflicted, I went aſtray, but now I keepe thy word: and as the Apoſtle Paul alſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaith vpon his owne experience, and the reſt of the faithfull in whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> name he ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> We know, that al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things worke together for the beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto them that feare God. Not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I my ſelfe, but many others alſo do know this to be true. Which is as if a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14254:32"/> skilfull Phiſitian ſhould ſay vnto his ſicke patient; take this potion, though it be bitter, it is for your health, I haue found the proofe of it by long expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience: nay not onely I my ſelfe, but all we Phyſitians doe know it to be ſo: and yet the patient would beleeue none of them, but himſelfe. Oh what a great note of infidelitie is within vs? how had we neede to ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it?</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, how often haue we heard this promiſe of our Sauiour Chriſt;<note place="margin">Math. 6 33.</note> Firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God, and his righteouſnes; and all outward things ſhal be miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you: and that alſo of the Apoſtle Paul vnto Timothie,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> Godlines is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vnto all things, which hath the promiſe of this life, and of that that is to come: yet let vs be in any want, and it is a wonder to ſee, how hardly or not at all we with cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe depend vpon Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14254:33"/> vntill ſuch time as we can ſee, how to prouide for our ſelues. Let o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men come, and ſay what they will, and what they haue found by experience in themſelues, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers concerning the truth of this, we doe not almoſt regard it, or take any comfort in it: ſo full of vnbeleefe are we, &amp; ſo common a thing is it in the matters of God, to giue credit to none but to our ſelues: as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. Thomas ſaith of himſelfe here.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs come to the matter of our ſaluation:<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.10</note> if Satan the accuſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the brethren, and our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doe ſet before our eies the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our ſinnes, and preſſe vs ſomewhat therewith; though we be heartily ſory for them, &amp; do weep bitterly,<note place="margin">Math. 26 75.</note> as Peter did at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his fall, and do wiſh a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times that we had neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them, &amp; thus trauell &amp; groane vnder the heauy burden of them, as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14254:33"/> that that is able to preſſe vs down vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottom of hell, and vnfainedly turne from them vnto God, ſaying with Dauid, Haue mercie vpon me,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.1.</note> O God, according to thy louing kindneſſe: according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy compaſſions put away mine iniquites: yet how hard a matter is it then to finde th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in our hearts, which we ſay with our mouth, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the forgiuenes of my ſinnes; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the day of temptation, and in the howre of death: though wee haue oftentimes before heard the bleſſed ſaying of the Apoſtle, This is a true ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and by all meanes worthy to be receiued, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners: and that comfortable voice of our Sauiour Chriſt, Come vnto me all ye that are wearie,<note place="margin">Matth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and I will eaſe you.</p>
            <p>This then we ſee is no new thing, for men not to beleeue ſundry parts
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14254:34"/> of Gods word brought vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the miniſterie of diuers of his faithful ſeruants, by reaſon of the great vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and hardnes of heart that is in them: whereby it commeth to paſſe that their owne vnderſtanding doth more preuaile with them to diſtruſt, then the teſtimonie of many to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. How then had we neede to find out this vnbeleefe in our ſelues: which when we haue done, we are not to iudge too hardly of our ſelues, ſeeing that it is ſo common: but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lament &amp; bewaile it, &amp; ſeeke vnto Chriſt to be holpen of it, who is the author and finiſher of our faith:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.2.</note> and ſay with the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.5.</note> Lord increaſe our faith: and with the man in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 9.24.</note> Lord I beleue, helpe my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe.</p>
            <p>And if there be ſuch great ſtreams of vnbeleefe in Gods children, till they be holpen of it, what a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſea, thinke you, is there of it in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14254:34"/> the wicked? whereby it commeth to paſſe, that they are filled with all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme and prophannes; caſting the word of God behinde their backs, ſo that let neuer ſo many learned and godly men, witneſſe the truth vnto them for their amendment, they will beleeue no more, then they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined before hand with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Let vs pray to God for them, that they may haue better mindes, euen deſirous to beleeue; and then ſhall they be holpen in time, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. Thomas was. And for our ſelues, let vs labour to haue teachable hearts, that we may reuerence &amp; giue credit vnto them, who in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our ſaluation know more then we doe: and haue in the matter of faith a great deale more experience then we our ſelues. That ſo it may come to paſſe, of what minde ſo euer we haue beene before, that when Gods faithfull ſeruants, whome we
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14254:35"/> ſhould eſteeme and truſt, they ſhall tell vs ſo and ſo: whether for Gods iudgements, or for his promiſes, or for the direction of our liues, we may beleeue, and obey them. Then ſhall we come to faith, and be confirmed in it:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17.</note> for he that regardeth inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is in the way of life.</p>
            <p>And if in other matters we thinke it reaſonable, that we ſhould beleeue thoſe, that haue more knowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues; yea euen cleane contrarie to that, that we thought before: as for the matter of our health we beleeue many skilfull Phyſitians for the ſtate of our bodies, and many expert law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers for the ſtate of our lands and goods; why ſhould we not then in matters of diuinitie, and for the ſtate of our ſoules, giue more credit to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny skilfull Diuines then to our ſelues. Eſpecially when as the generall rule holdeth as well in that, as in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcience: that euery skilfull man
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14254:35"/> is to be credited in his owne arte and facultie: our reaſon is more corrupt in this, then in any other thing, and therefore there is more cauſe that we ſhould beleeue others, then our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Therefore as in other matters, when we are doubtfull, we conferre with them that haue more skill and knowledge, and giue credit vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrarie to our owne thoughts, and we are readie to relie vpon them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then vpon our ſelues: So let vs doe in matters of faith, and let vs not offer Gods ſeruants and our ſelues this great wrong, that we wil beleeue all men in other things, ſauing then in this. It is too much, that we haue done it ſo often alreadie, let vs not continue in it, that we ſhould come to the Church, and heare Gods word preached, and goe away not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it: and come againe the next day, and then depart away, as full of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14254:36"/> vnbeleefe, as before: and thus from day to day, &amp; ſo ſtill be of this mind, that whatſoeuer men ſay, we will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue none but our ſelues, thinking that we haue reaſon as well as they, and therefore vnles we can conceiue it by reaſon, we will not admit it, whatſoeuer they ſay.</p>
            <p>For faith is aboue reaſon, therfore we muſt beleeue the ſeruants of God in things, whereof we can conceiue no reaſon: nay reaſon is againſt faith, and there is nothing in vs more to hinder vs from beleeuing, then to harken to our owne reaſon.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 2.14.</note> For the naturall man (by his beſt reaſon) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth not the things of the ſpirit of God: for they are fooliſhnes vnto him: neither can he know them (by his owne wit) becauſe they are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcerned: that is, by a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inlightning of the ſprit of God. So that matters of faith we can not only not by reaſon comprehend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14254:36"/> but they ſeeme fooliſhnes vnto all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that will no further giue credit vnto things, then they be demonſtrated by reaſon: which made the Apoſtles, when the women came from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, &amp; told them that Chriſt was riſen, not onely not to beleeue them, but that their words ſeemed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a fained thing,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.11</note> and a meere fable that had no truth in it: and therefore Chriſt ſaith in the Goſpel,<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> If any man will follow me, let him forſake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that is, his owne reaſon moſt of all, that ſo he may beleeue others contrary vnto it.</p>
            <p>And this is that which is ſo highly commended by the ſpirit of God in our father Abraham,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.1</note> that he aboue all hope (that reaſon could affoard him) beleeued vnder hope, that he ſhould be the father of many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for he conſidered not his owne bodie, which was now dead (that is, void of ſtrength, and vnmeete to get
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14254:37"/> children) beeing almoſt an hundred yeares old: neither the deadneſſe of Sarahs wombe: neither did he doubt of the promiſe of God through vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe; but was ſtrengthned in faith, and gaue glorie to God, beeing fully aſſured, that he that had promiſed it, was able to doe it: where we ſee, that renouncing his owne reaſon, which would haue held him in vnbeleefe, he reſted vpon the truth and power of God, and ſo beleeued aboue that by reaſon could be ſhewed him, or he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to conceiue: and ſo muſt we doe alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.3.</note>The Apoſtle ſaith, that through faith we vnderſtand, that the world was ordained by the word of God, and that the things which we ſee, are not made of things which did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: that is, that this great &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull frame of the world was made of nothing, is a matter not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by any reaſon, but onely
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14254:37"/> by faith: which made not onely the Epicures, but alſo ſome of the wiſeſt Philoſophers, to hold, that the world was not eternall: for it was vnto them a principle in reaſon, that of nothing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omes nothing, neither can you ſo multiplie nothing, that there ſhould come any thing of it. Therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that he that will hold, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat all theſe things, which we ſee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eauen and earth were made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing, he muſt beleeue it aboue all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſon.</p>
            <p>And who can by any reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eiue the truth of this article of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith, The reſurrection of the bodie? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, that theſe very bodies of ours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeing turned into duſt and aſhes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſame in euery part and member <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould be raiſed vp againe. Some of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e wiſer ſort of the Heathen did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>owledge the immortalitie of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule, and that there was a place of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y for them that liued well, and of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14254:38"/> paine for them that ſwarued from the rules of right reaſon, after death. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the ſame bodies of men ſhould riſe againe, they did not ſo much as once dreame of it, becauſe they could not comprehend it by any reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore in that matter we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue others aboue all reaſon.</p>
            <p>The like is to be ſaide of almes, which hath a promiſe of increaſe: ſo that by giuing to the poore we ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not looſe any thing, but gaine: which is a thing contrarie to reaſon, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more a man ſhould giue away from himſelfe, the more he ſhould inric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe: and therefore few doe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue it, which maketh them coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tous and hard hearted, and to be wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to depart from nothing, lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they ſhould want themſelues: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſpecially to be moſt hard hearted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> their poore brethren in the times o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcarſitie and want, when they ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be moſt liberall, and by that meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14254:38"/> beſt prouide for themſelues: which S. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo fully perſwaded of, that he doth commend it vnto vs by an excellent compariſon, ſaying,<note place="margin">2. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reape alſo ſparingly: and he that ſoweth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, ſhall reape alſo liberally. Where he compareth almes vnto ſowing of ſeede: the more a man ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the more he reapeth by Gods bleſſing: the more a man giueth, the more he receiueth by Gods promiſe: the one we ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the times of dearth and ſcarſitie, to ſow moſt: the other we comprehend by faith, which maketh the beleeuer in the hardeſt times, to be moſt liberall. Thus we ſee, what vnbeleefe is in vs, in that we giue no credit vnto others, any further then we can conceiue a reaſon of it: which is the ſame, that was in S. Thomas, and yet he was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of it, and ſo may we by the ſame
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14254:39"/> grace of God, if we will learne this leſſon; that in the time of temptation we beleeue others aboue our ſelues: which if we doe not, it is the next way to remain in vnbeleefe for euer: but if we can come vnto this, there is hope of vs in time.</p>
            <p>THe 2. degree of Thomas his vnbeleefe, appeares in this; that he wold not only not beleeue this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus often told him, diuers times, &amp; by ſundrie credible perſons, but he will beleeue none but himſelfe: for he ſaith in plaine words, Except I ſee in his hands, the print of the nayls, I will not beleeue it. Which is, as if he had ſaid; you indeed tel me, that you haue ſeen Chriſt riſen again, &amp; ſo do diuers others; I haue heard theſe things ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but I haue not yet ſeene him my ſelfe; what others haue ſeene, that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines not vnto me, vnleſſe I ſee him my ſelfe, I will not beleeue it. This therefore is further to be conſidered,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14254:39"/> becauſe ſomtime it fals out, that there is good cauſe, why we ſhould not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue a thing ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> often, &amp; by many.</p>
            <p>And if they be of any good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, though there be no cauſe in truth to ſuſpect them, yet it may ſeeme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that there is ſome: and hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it commeth to paſſe, that ſome in their vnbeleefe take exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Preachers, and thinke that they haue ſome cauſe, why they ſhould not beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the things that they haue preached vnto them, though in truth there be none. But yet to be altogether of this mind, that S. Thomas was here in this matter, that we will beleeue none in the world, but our ſelues, that ſeemeth to be ſuch a thing as wanteth all colour of reaſon. And yet thus vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is vnbeleefe, as we ſee moſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this example: for he ſaith very peremptorily, that vnleſſe I my ſelfe doe ſee in his hands the print of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14254:40"/> nayles, I will not beleeue it. He doth not ſay, vnles better men then you doe tell me ſo; or vnles I heare more in number; or vnles I heare better reaſon for this matter, then I doe yet, I will not beleeue it: but if all men in the world tell me of it neuer ſo often, vnles I ſee him mine owne ſelfe, I will beleeue none of them: which is, as if he had ſaid, In this caſe I will beleeue my ſelfe, and no bodie els.</p>
            <p>We ſee then whether vnbeleefe will driue vs, if we giue place to it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that we ſhall beleeue none but our ſelues. And indeede ſo it is in all ſorts, in whome it raigneth, they will beleeue no more from any man, then they can perſwade themſelues by their owne reaſon: vnto that they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatly ſticke againſt all men: and ſo are not aſhamed to ſay, I will beleeue none of you all; I will beleeue mine owne ſelfe, and further I will not be lead by any: no man ſhall draw me to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14254:40"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleeue that, which mine owne rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon tells me not. And thus they ſo much abound in their owne ſenſe through vnbeleefe, that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues, that they haue more reaſon for that they hold, then all other men haue for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            <p>And ſo let men ſay neuer ſo much againſt that, which they haue concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues, they ſtil imagine, that they haue ſome thing to ſay againſt it, and ſome reaſon, why they ſhould not beleeue them. And this is moſt true, not onely in matters of faith, but for life and conuerſation: which is the cauſe, both that Papiſts and other heretikes are ſo obſtinately addicted to their errors; and alſo wicked men ſo altogether wedded vnto their ſinnes; that neither the one, nor the other can be reclaimed from them. And therefore when men haue ſaide what they can, they will not giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:14254:41"/> ouer, for they haue determined to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue none but themſelues: &amp; of this minde will they be, till God ridde them of their vnbeleefe: and then the ſaying of Chriſt ſhal be verified vpon them,<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.29.</note> Bleſſed are they, that haue not ſeene, and haue beleeued: that is, they ſhall beleeue others, beſides them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſo bleſſed ſhall they be: as indeede this is the way to faith, and ſo to bleſſednes, to diſtruſt our ſelues, and to beleeue the ſeruants of God, ſpeaking vnto vs in his name: of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt hath ſaide,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 20 40.</note> He that receiueth you, and your doctrine, receiueth me.</p>
            <p>And that we might come vnto this, we are to remember, that true faith yeildes vnto the bare word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God againſt our owne reaſon; and ſo giueth glory vnto God,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.20.</note> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth, acknowledging, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerencing his truth, mercy, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where we can ſee no reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14254:41"/> it, and ſo prayſing him for the ſame, and reſting in it. Which we ſee to be true in Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not onely in the birth of Iſaac, which was beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the courſe of nature, and ſo aboue all reaſon: but alſo in the offering vp of the ſaid I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac his ſonne, whom he loued, and in whom he receiued the promiſes, euen that with him God would eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his couenant,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and with his ſeede after him for euer: and therefore take away him, and take away all, and the hope of all: and yet at the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, he was contented to offer him vp for a burnt offering in mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Moriah: which he did by faith,<note place="margin">chap. 22</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.</note> for he conſidered that God was able to raiſe him vp eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the dead: and ſo he meaſured the performance of the promiſes of God, not by his owne reaſon, though neuer ſo great, but by the truth and power of God.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaide of Noah
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14254:42"/> concerning the building of the Arke, of whom it is ſaid;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſ. 17.</note> that by faith he beeing warned of God of the things which were not as yet ſeene, mooued with reuerence, prepared the Arke to the ſauing of his houſhold. In which matter if he had conſulted with fleſh &amp; blood, and conferred with his own reaſon, he ſhould neuer haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken ſo great a matter. For how could he thereby imagine that all the world ſhould be drowned except his family, and that they ſhould be ſaued, and all the reſt periſh: when by the ſpace of 120 yeares, he both prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Arke, and preaching their deſtruction, not one man or woman would beleeue it, beſides his owne family of eight perſons; might not he haue thought that he was deceiued rather then they all. And how could he haue hope that fowre men ſhould gouerne ſo great a veſſell, wherein ſhould be male &amp; female at the leaſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14254:42"/> of euery liuing thing vpon the earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd in the ayre, with ſufficient proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for them all by the ſpace of an whole yeare: and that not in the great Ocean ſea, but when the whole world was a ſea. And where could he thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o haue meanes to take and bring in all theſe fowles of the heauen, and beaſts of the earth? and how could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey attend vpon them all to feede them, and to doe all things neceſſarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto them? And many more things might be put into his head, to cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im to deſiſt from this worke, as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing impoſſible: and no doubt he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ſubiect vnto many of theſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch like temptations, but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle ſheweth vs, how he ouercame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, euen by faith: whoſe nature and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ropertie is, to relie vpon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andement and promiſe of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue all reaſon, and contrarie vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t.</p>
            <p>But on the otherſide vnbeleefe,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14254:43"/> which is contrarie vnto faith, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth wholly and onely vpon reaſon; in ſo much that vnleſſe they can ſee ſome reaſon, how that may be done, that is ſaide, and promiſed, they will not beleeue it, they thinke it impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they reiect it as an vnreaſonable thing. A moſt liuely patterne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue in that great man of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, in the daies of Ahab king of Iſrael: at what time by reaſon of the fiege of the king of Aram, there was ſuch an extreame famine, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did eate their owne children.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. king. 6.28.</note> Then the prophet Eliſha did prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie vnto them great plentie on the ſudden, euen the next day following. To whom this great prince,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hap. 7.2.</note> on whoſe hand the king leaned, anſwered, and ſaid, Though the Lord would make windows in heauen, could this thing come to paſſe? as though he had ſaid, this is impoſſible, though the Lord ſhal raine downe corne from heauen
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14254:43"/> among vs? for he could not conceiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y any reaſon, how either the ſiege <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould be ſo ſuddenly raiſed; or if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, how it ſhould come to paſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat corne beeing ſo vnreaſonably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare to day, it ſhould be ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingly cheape to morrow. But God verified his owne word vnto them at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he time appointed, and this man ſaw it with his eyes, but neuer taſted of it, becauſe of his vnbeleefe. For the king appointed him to be gouernor, and to ſit in the gate of the citie, to ſee the corne ſold to the people, who ſo thronged,<note place="margin">verſ. 20.</note> that they troad vpon him, and there he died.</p>
            <p>The whole world is full of this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, that they will beleeue no more then their owne reaſon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades them vnto: and that that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt their reaſon they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to croſſe it, though it be neuer ſo true. For how many are there, that haue ſet downe with themſelues, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14254:44"/> whatſoeuer the Preachers ſay, they haue determined a courſe, which they thinke, they haue good reaſon for: in that they minde to continue, beyond that they will not goe; they are ſo ſetled, that out of it, they will not be remooued; they hope they are not now to learne, they are too old to be taught; they truſt that they haue not liued ſo long for nothing; they haue wit and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as well as other men; and ſo that that they haue conceiued they will ſticke vnto, that courſe they haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into, they purpoſe to continue in, and in that they minde to liue and die; and this courſe they hold for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine both of faith and manners, for duties to God and to men; and thus they will beleeue none but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and their owne reaſon.</p>
            <p>And thus though they come to the Church from day to day, they come not to learne any thing, they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14254:44"/> haue determined beforehand what they minde to doe. They will learne of no man, they can teach themſelues ſufficiently. Whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that though they daily heare their ſinnes rebuked, they will amend nothing; and the iudgements of God denounced againſt them, they will beleeue nothing: they thinke, they haue better reaſon for their doings, then any man can haue againſt them. And if they be called vpon to increaſe in knowledge and godlines, and ſo to goe on to perfection; they ſtand ſtill at a ſtay, and thinke it not neceſſarie; they like well of their owne doings, and no man ſhall remooue them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, they will beleeue none but themſelues: vnleſſe I ſee reaſon for it mine owne ſelfe, I will not beleeue you.</p>
            <p>Thus through vnbeleefe the word is choaked in the greateſt part of the hearers, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14254:45"/> in the parable of the ſeede: and it profiteth them not one whit, no more then it did the Iewes, when it was preached vnto them, becauſe it was not mixed with faith in them that heard it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 4.2.</note> And ſo that is the very cauſe, why in this long time of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, there hath bin ſo little good done, euen the great vnbeleefe that raigneth in men euery where. Of which the Prophet Iſai had too great experience in his time in them to whom he preached, and doth with great griefe complaine of it, when he crieth out thus pathetically, who will beleeue our report? &amp; to whom is the arme of the Lord reuealed?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. 53.1.</note> meaning, that none would beleeue it, but thoſe whoſe hearts God touched by his holy Sprit. And thus by their doings men doe too apparently ſhew, that though they doe not vtter it with their mouthes, yet they ſay it with their hearts, that let men ſay what
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14254:45"/> they will, becauſe as they thinke they haue ſome reaſon againſt it, they will beleeue none but themſelues.</p>
            <p>Let vs labour to ſee this vnbeleefe in our ſelues in any meaſure, that we haue it, and be ſorie for it, and ſtriue againſt it: and pray God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs, and helpe vs. And that we might this way be holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs not be too much addicted to our reaſon, &amp; meaſure things by it: for our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon beeing corrupt, it doth not onely not further vs vnto faith, but doth ſomtimes hinder vs from it; not onely becauſe faith is of things aboue reaſon, but contrary vnto it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the matter of our ſaluation we muſt be ſo farre from being addicted to our owne will and reaſon, as that we muſt vtterly deny it, that we might beleeue: as the Apoſtle Saint Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ſhould haue done here: &amp; haue ſaid, though this that you tell me be a matter impoſſible in mine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14254:46"/> and reaſon, and I cannot poſſibly conceiue how it ſhould be: yet becauſe ſo many of you beeing of conſcience to ſpeake the truth, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it.</p>
            <p>And thus did Abraham concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the promiſe, which God had made vnto him:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 4.20.</note> for it is ſaid, that he did not deſpiſe or reaſon againſt the promiſe of God through vnbeleefe: where theſe two are ioyned together as ſubordinate, &amp; come helping one the other, namely, reaſon and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and not reaſon and faith. So that if we hearken to reaſon, it will cauſe vs to doubt rather then beleeue: and the next way to beleeue, is not to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten or giue credit vnto the diſputes &amp; doubts that reaſon will miniſter vnto vs. For it is able to obiect many things againſt that that we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: and therefore if we will be Chriſts diſciples, we muſt denie no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely all our ſinnefull affections tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:14254:46"/> might draw vs from obeying, his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but our reaſon eſpecially which might diſſwade fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeuing it. That when our reaſon ſhall tell vs one thing, as that we may continue in our ſinnes a while longer, we may repent at leiſure, and be ſaued well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: and that the way to heauen is not ſo ſtraight, as men ſpeake of and then we ſhall heare the contrarie out of Gods word daily, we muſt beleeue that contrarie to our reaſon, if we will be ſaued. For Thomas remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in this vnbeleefe, he might haue periſhed for euer, but that Chriſt had mercie on him extraordinarily, and yeilded vnto his vnbeleefe for the good of the Church; that for his ſake, he might ſhew himſelfe vnto his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles after his reſurection another time.</p>
            <p>Therefore firſt of all let vs pray to God to ſanctifie our reaſon, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten it by his holy ſpirit, that we
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14254:47"/> may be capable of the myſteries of word of God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.18.</note> as Dauid doth, Open mine eies, that I may ſee the wonders of thy law. And ſecondly when we come to heare, and read the word of God, let vs bring theſe minds with vs, that what reaſon ſoeuer we ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue for our opinions &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings before, when we ſhall heare the contrary auouched by the ſeruants of God, &amp; prooued out of the ſcripture, we giue them ouer &amp; credit them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue our ſelues. And let vs renounce that reaſon of ours, that ſhall miniſter vnto vs any thing againſt that that hath been taught vs out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not harken vnto it. For if we ſhould hold the Angels of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accurſed,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 1.8.</note> if they deliuer any thing to vs contrary to the written word of God: then much more ſhould we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe and denie our owne reaſon, that ſhould ſuggeſt any thing vnto vs contrary to the ſame: and let vs no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:14254:47"/> after ſo long time of preaching be ſtil of this minde, that we will beleeue none but our ſelues.</p>
            <p>A Third degree of the vnbeleefe of S. Thomas appeareth in this, that he ſaith, Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nailes, and put my finger into the print of the nailes, and put my hand into his ſide, I will not beleeue it. For, as though it had not bene ſufficient that he had ſayd, that he would beleeue none of them; nor any other that ſhould tell him as much as they did: he would beleeue none but himſelfe: he further addeth, that vnles he might ſee in his hands and feete the print of the nailes, and put in his finger into them, he would not beleeue it. Which is as if he had ſaide, if I may not onely ſee himſelfe, as you ſay you haue done: but may be ſure of it, and therefore may alſo ſee in his body theſe markes, that he had on the croſſe, and eſpecially if I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14254:48"/> may come ſo neere vnto him, that I may feele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and put my finger into them, I will beleeue it; otherwiſe I will not. So that he will no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleeue, for all their ſayings then his outward ſenſes ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him; and namely, his ſight and feeling: if I may ſee and feele, I will beleeue, and till then I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
            <p>O wonderfull infidelitie: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in one that was ſo neere Chriſt, and had beene ſo long time conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with him. For what if Chriſt had neuer appeared vnto him, nor vnto any other of the Apoſtles? was it not ſufficient vnto them, that he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before in their hearing ſaide; that he ſhould be put to death,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atth. 16.31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 17.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d 26.32.</note> and the third day riſe againe: And that they were charged to ſhew no man that viſion which they ſaw vpon the mountaine, vntill he was riſen againe from the dead: and after I am riſen
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14254:48"/> againe, I will goe before you into Galile. Should they not haue beene left without excuſe in their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe? Seeing they had heard it from his owne mouth ſo often before his death: and now after his reſurrection diuers credible women did tell them that they had ſeene him riſen againe, according as he had often told them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, if he were of that minde, and thought that he had good reaſon for it, that he would not beleeue, vnles he did thus ſee &amp; feele him why may not other be of the ſame minde too? and ſo Chriſt ſhould haue remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon the earth vnto this day, and not haue aſcended into heauen: or els often ſince he ſhould haue deſcended to ſhew himſelfe to thoſe that ſhould beleeue: if none would beleeue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they ſhould ſee and feele. Moreouer after that he had thus ſeen him and felt him himſelfe, would he not haue thought it ſtrange, if others
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14254:49"/> would not haue beleeued him, when he preached vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt? why then doth he make ſuch a ſtraight rule to himſelfe?</p>
            <p>Surely that in him we might ſee a patterne of that great weaknes that is in vs, and how full of vnbeleefe we be: and a liuely example of the great mercie of Chriſt in bearing with ſinners in the ſame: and by all meanes putting them out of the ſame in time, that they might be ſaued.</p>
            <p>And why doth he ſay thus rather then any thing elſe, Except I may ſee and feele, &amp;c. Are theſe two ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſuch ſure iudges of the truth, that they cannot be deceiued? May not a man thinke, that he ſeeth and feeleth that, which he doth not? and may he not againe doubt, whether he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and feeleth that, which indeede he doth? How came it to paſſe that when Eliſha had cauſed water to come miraculouſly into a vally of the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14254:49"/> wildernes, for the Kings of Iſrael, of Iudah, and of Edom, that the Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites when as earely in the morning the ſunne roſe vpon the water, and they ſaw the water as redde as blood ouer againſt them; they ſaid, This is blood: the kings are ſurely ſlaine, and one hath ſmitten an other: but when they came to the hoſt of Iſrael they found it otherwiſe. And as the ſight of theſe men deceiued them, ſo did the feeling of Iſaac deceiue him in his old age. For his ſonne Iaakob com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto him in the perſon and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of his elder brother Eſau to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſing: when he felt the roughnes of his necke and hands, which Rebekah had couered wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h skinnes, he iudged by his feeling that it was Eſau. For he ſaid, Come neere my ſonne, that I may feele thee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou be my ſonne Eſau or no; &amp; when he had felt him he ſaid, The hands are the hands of Eſau.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:14254:50"/>
            <p>Thus wee ſee that ſight and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling may eaſily be deceiued: and yet this is the nature of vnbeleefe, to giue credit more vnto theſe deceiueable ſenſes, then to many other things, that are moſt ſure and certaine. And many men in matters of faith will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beleeue nothing, vntill ſuch time, as they ſee and feele them: and therefore when they are taught what in heauen is prepared for them that ſerue God; what in hell for them that diſobey him: they are readie to ſay, who hath ſeen them? giuing vs to vnderſtand, that they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them, vntill they either ſee them, or feele them themſelues. Was not this vnbeleefe vniuerſally ſpread ouer the face of the whole world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the flood, when Noah the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of righteoſnes declared vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the iudgment of God, that ſhould come vpon them for their ſinnes; &amp; namly, that God would bring a flood
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14254:50"/> of waters vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth to deſtroy all fleſh wherin was the breath of life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heauen, becauſe all fleſh had corrupted his way, and the earth was filled with cruelty; and thus he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued preaching an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred &amp; twentie yeares: But none of them beleeued it though they ſaw him alſo all this while preparing the Arke for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of himſelfe and his family. And therefore they continued ſtill in their impenitencie, and in their ſinnes, till the flood came and tooke them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And ſo they ſaid to Noah, ſome in their thoghts, ſome in their words, as Thomas did here in an other caſe to the Apoſtles: You ſay that the world ſhalbe drowned, but except we ſee the raine come in ſuch meaſure, and feele it, we will not beleeue it.</p>
            <p>And was not the like infidelity after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in all the men of Sodom where iuſt Lot liued, and was vexed with their vncleanely conuerſation: for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14254:51"/> which he denounced Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt them: and at the laſt by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reuelation of the Angels that were ſent vnto them, he ſaide vnto his ſonnes in law which had maried his daughters, Ariſe, go out of this place, for the Lord wil deſtroy this citie; but he ſeemed to his ſonnes in law as though he had mocked. Thus they would not beleeue it, becauſe they ſaw it not, nor any likelihood of it, till fire and brimſtone came downe from heauen, and fell vpon them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed them. And ſo they being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and the citie ouerthrowne, they were made an example vnto them that after ſhould liue vngodly, and which would not beleeue the truth of Gods iudgements againſt ſinne in the mouthes of his ſeruants any further then they ſhall ſee and feele themſelues.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how common this is among all vnbeleeuers, ſo farre as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14254:51"/> preuaileth with them, that they will beleeue nothing that is threatned againſt ſinne any further, then they ſee and feele it themſelues. When in the famin of Samaria there was exceeding great plentie againſt the next day promiſed by Eliſha the Prophet, did not one of the Princes ſay; when I ſee it, I will beleeue it, and not before. Whereupon this anſwere was giuen vnto him, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, thou ſhalt ſee it with thine eies, but thou ſhalt not eate thereof. And ſo vnbeleefe diſcredits not only the threatnings, but the promiſes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they can ſee them with their eies, and feele them with their hands: of which we ſhall ſpeake more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Doth not S. Peter ſay, that there ſhal come mockers in theſe laſt daies, which will walke after their luſt, and ſay, where is the promiſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming? for ſince the fathers died, all
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14254:52"/> things continue alike fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the creation. Wherein he ſheweth how men through vnbeleef will make a mocke of Chriſts ſecond comming, &amp; of the end of the world, and of the day of iudgement: becauſe with their eyes they doe not ſee any ſuch thing likely to come to paſſe: when they ſhall ſee ſome great alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in heauen &amp; in earth bending that way, they will beleeue it, and no ſooner, nor any further.</p>
            <p>And we finde by experience the truth of this daily in many, that they will beleeue nothing of this matter any further, then they can ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And our Sauiour Chriſt in the Goſpel hath foretold, and forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs of this, when as he ſaith: As it was in the dayes of Noah,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k. 17.26.</note> ſo ſhall it be in the dayes of the ſonne of man: they eate, they dranke, they bought, they ſolde, they married wiues, and gaue in marriage, vnto the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14254:52"/> day that Noah went into the Arke, and the flood came and deſtroyed them all.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe alſo, as it was in the daies of Lot, they eate, they dranke, they planted, they built: but in the day that Lot went out of Sodom, it rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fire and brimſtone from heauen, and deſtroyed them all: after theſe inſamples ſhall it be, when the ſonne of man ſhall be reuealed: that is, not onely it ſhall come ſuddenly and all things ſhall continue in their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie courſe: but men ſhall then giue themſelues to all pleaſure and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: and ſhall neither beleeue it, nor thinke of it, till it come: as the men of the old world did not: of whome the Euangeliſt S. Matthew ſaith, that they knew nothing, till the flood came and tooke them all away: ſo ſhal alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be. They knew nothing, not that they had not heard of it, for Noah did
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14254:53"/> preach vnto them an 120. yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but they did not beleeue it, nor regard it, becauſe they ſaw it not: euen ſo ſhall it be towards the end of the world: though they haue heard of theſe things an hundred times, yet they wil know nothing til they ſee it.</p>
            <p>And not onely this ſinne raigneth in the wicked, that they will beleeue no more of the promiſes and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; of the ioyes of heauen, &amp; pains of hell, then they can ſee &amp; feele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and ſo becauſe they do neither of them yet, they will beleeue none of them; let men ſay what they will, and neuer ſo long: and ſo they goe on in their ſinnes, and liue thereafter: which is greatly to be lamented. But alſo if we will examine our ſelues, &amp; other men, we ſhall finde, that this was in our ſelues, and in them, til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord had mercie vpon vs. That though we had often heard that God was iuſt, and would puniſh ſinne, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:14254:53"/> we preſumed otherwiſe, and did not beleeue it, becauſe we eſcaped a while in our ſinnes, and did not ſee and feele the truth of it in our ſelues: and by that meanes went on, and were hardened in our ſinnes. And ſo that was verified in vs, as well as in others, which the Lord complaineth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f by his Prophet;<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> Theſe things haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou done, and I held my tongue: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore thou thoughteſt that I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke thee: but I will reprooue thee, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſet them in order before thee.</p>
            <p>And thus not only before our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng, infidelity did wholly beare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſway in vs: but alſo ſince that time great remnant of it ſtill remaineth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vs: ſo that in many things we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleeue no further, then we ſee, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ele, eſpecially in the time of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion: for if we be in any great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e,<note place="margin">Iob</note> and then if there be a meſſenger God ſent vnto vs, or an interpreter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his word, one of a thouſand, as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihu
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14254:54"/> calleth him: who ſhal bid vs be of good comfort, and put our truſt in God, he will helpe vs and deliuer vs in his good time: and declare vnto vs many promiſes of his word, to that ende. We then, if wee want meanes to help our ſelues, we are ready to ſay, O but I ſee not how, and which way that ſhould be. So that if we did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vſe the promiſed helpe that we might feele it, or had means to bring it to paſſe, that we might ſee it, we ſay, we wold beleeue it, or els not. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our faith goeth no further to comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, then our ſenſes of ſeeing and fee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling. And this is too true, in what af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fliction ſoeuer we be, either of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, ſickeneſſe, or any other di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>And this vnbeleefe of ours is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much the more dangerous and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more deepely rooted in vs, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> though we haue had experience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods goodnes towards our ſelues i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:14254:54"/> time paſt, wherein we may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber how he hath holpen and deliuered vs beyond all that we could foreſee, or haue any hope of: yet at another time we truſt him and his worde, no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we can ſee our ſelues. Thus the people of Iſrael doubted of the power of God, whether he would giue them fleſh in the wildernes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſire, though they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad ſeene his power before in giuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> water out of the hard rock: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Dauid ſpeaketh after this manner, They temped God in their hearts,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.18.</note> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>equiring meate for their luſt: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pake againſt God alſo, ſaying, Can God prepare a table in the wildernes? Behold, he ſmote the rocke, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ater guſhed out, and the ſtreames <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uerflowed: can he giue bread alſo? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r prepare fleſh for his people? Where he aggrauateth their ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f infidelitie, in that they ſeeing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore how he beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d all hope brought
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14254:55"/> water plentifully out of the rocke to ſupplie their want, they did now doubt that they ſhould haue no fleſh, though Moſes had promiſed it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them from God, becauſe they could not ſee how in the wildernes ſuch aboundance ſhould be prepared for ſo great a people, that euery one might haue enough.</p>
            <p>And we our ſelues are ſubiect to the like, not onely in theſe outward things, and are therein too much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlead, becauſe we relie wholly vpon our outward ſenſes: but alſo in the matter of our ſaluation, therein our vnbeleefe doth eſpecially ſhew it ſelfe, ſo that we can hardly or not at all beleeue any thing beyonde our ſenſe and feeling. For when we are humbled vnder the weighty hand of God with the ſight of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſinnes, and haue the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Gods wrath vpon vs for them in any meaſure: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> though we heare
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14254:55"/> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable promiſes of the goſpel made to all that vnfainedly turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> As there is no condemnation to them, that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.16.</note> And if you will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly walke and make your ſelues cleane from them, and take away the euill of your works from before your eies; ceaſe to doe euil, &amp; learne to doe good: though your ſinnes were as crimſon, they ſhall be made white as ſnow: though they were red as ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et, they ſhalbe as white as wooll: that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, if you leaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I am readie to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them, though they be neuer ſo many: and then we find by the grace of God, that we vtterly deteſt them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd are weary of them, as of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortable burden, &amp; haue caſt them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way from vs, as a filthie cloath: yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe we ſee not the light of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ountenance ſhining clearly vpon vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd haue not the feeling of his loue
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14254:56"/> powred into our hearts, wee cannot beleeue the pardon of them, as wee ought. And vnto all the promiſes, that are brought for our comfort, we are ready to obiect: alas, we haue no feeling of that, that is ſaid vnto vs. Which is as if we ſhould thus ſpeak; you ſay thus and thus vnto me, but I can haue no comfort in it: for vnles I ſee it, and feele it, I will not beleeue it. Which vnbeleefe though it be very great, yet Chriſt Ieſus doth beare with them a while in it, and helpe them of it in due ſeaſon, as he did his ſeruant Thomas the Apoſtle here.</p>
            <p>And truly as the Deuill did by Gods permiſſion thus farre preuaile with the Apoſtle S. Thomas that he was brought to this ſtraight, that without ſight and feeling he would not beleeue: So with this one temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his he hath ſo mightily preuailed againſt many of the beſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14254:56"/> ſeruants of god, that he hath brought them to a very low ebbe, euen almoſt to their wits ende. For beſides that he hath driuen them to this extremitie, which is very great, that they wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue no more of Gods fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, then they can ſee and feele in themſelues: he hath gained this alſo at their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, which is much more: that becauſe they haue no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, therefore they ſay they haue no faith: as though theſe two were both one, feeling and faith; or as though they were alwaies neceſſarily ioyned together.</p>
            <p>And hereupon haue come the great complaints and outcries, which ſome of them haue made againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in the time of their trouble: and not onely of thoſe, who haue groſly &amp; apparantly fallen into ſome ſinne, and therefore there was ſome manifeſt cauſe of it: but of thoſe alſo which haue liued blameleſly, neither
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14254:57"/> haue beene tainted with any great ſinne: And yet both of them in the time of their temptation haue vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many bitter words againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; as that they are altogether out of the fauour of God; that they are not in the number of them that ſhall be ſaued; they haue no part in Chriſt; they are none of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſuch like. And why ſo? for ſay they, they haue no ſight and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the fauour of God in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and therefore they haue no faith, neither can haue: for except they haue ſome feeling in their hearts, they cannot beleeue.</p>
            <p>And this temptation hath lien vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the conſcience of ſome more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily, and of others leſſe: vpon ſome longer, vpon others ſhorter time: euen as it hath pleaſed the Lord ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in wiſdome to trie the one, or in mercie to ſuccour the other. This was that that did ſo oppreſſe Dauid,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14254:57"/> as appeareth in many Pſalmes, that he was almoſt in deſpaire of himſelfe: when he ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.1.</note> How long wilt thou forget me for euer? how long wilt thou hide thy face from me? and will the Lord abſent himſelfe for euer?<note place="margin">and 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> and will he ſhew no more fauour? is his mercie cleane gone for euer? and doth his promiſe faile for euermore? hath God forgotten to be mercifull? and hath he ſhut vp his tender mercy in diſpleaſure: and, My God, my God,<note place="margin">and 22.1</note> why haſt thou forſaken me? and art ſo farre from my health, and from the voice of my roaring? I crie by day, but thou heareſt not: and by night, but haue no audience. And thus he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, till it pleaſed God for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and comfort to giue him victorie; partly by conſidering the former mercifull dealing of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelfe and others; partly by meditating vpon the conſtant truth of his promiſes, which made him at
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14254:58"/> the laſt truſt vnto him, and depend vpon him without any preſent helpe or feeling. And thus he endeth the 38. Pſalme, which he made to put himſelfe in remembrance of ſome great affliction of God, that was vpon him, and therefore intitles it a <hi>Pſalme of remembrance:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 38.</note> in which are many grieuous complaints both of his ſinnes, and of the puniſhment of them, without any feeling of preſent helpe and comfort; onely he ſaith, that he would waite vpon God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 15.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that he would ſhew himſelfe fauourable in time, though he had no preſent feeling of it. And ſo muſt we doe in the like caſe. But in the meane ſeaſon we ſee, that this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of vnbeleefe, that was in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. Thomas, that he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue no more, then he could ſee and feele, is and hath beene in others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and that all of vs are ſubiect vnto it more or leſſe.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:14254:58"/>
            <p>But that we may arme our ſelues ſufficiently againſt this grieuous temptation, and comfortably ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port our ſelues, when we ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; we muſt conſider that faith and feeling are not onely not all one, nor alwaies ioyned together: but alſo that they are many times ſeuered in the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: ſo that there is faith, where there is not, nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feeling: yea, that the greateſt faith ſometimes is, where there is no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at all. And to this ende we muſt remember, what the Apoſtle ſaith of the nature of faith, It is the ground of things which are hoped for, and the euidence of things, which are not ſeene. Where he ſaith, that faith is of ſuch things, as we ſee not, and of thoſe things which are but hoped for, and we as yet haue not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſſeſſion and feeling of them, and yet we beleeue them. And this he prooueth by moſt excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14254:59"/> when as firſt of all he addeth, Through faith we vnderſtand,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſ. 3.</note> that the world was ordained by the word of God: ſo that the things which we ſee are not made of things which did appeare: that is, we know by faith, that the whole world was made of nothing, and this verely we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: but who did, or euer could ſee this? Therefore we doe, and muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that which we haue not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can ſee: &amp; ſo we haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it by faith, and not by ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſ. 7.</note>Secondarily, he thus ſpeaketh there of the faith of Noah: that he beeing warned of God of the things, which were as yet not ſeene, mooued with reuerence prepared the Arke to the ſauing of his houſhold. Where two things are noted, that he beleued that which he could not ſee: 1. that all the world ſhould be drowned for their ſinnes: 2. that by repentance and faith himſelfe had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fauour with god, &amp; ſhould be ſaued in the waters: &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14254:59"/> he made the Arke according to Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement long before he ſaw the flood, or any toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it, that he might be ſaued in it. And ſo he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the iudgement of God to come vpon the wicked, and ſaluation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed himſelfe, though he could not ſee, nor haue any preſent feeling of either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this is that operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith which it muſt haue in vs; euen to cauſe vs to beleeue both the threatnings of gods iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts againſt impenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſinners, &amp; the promiſes of ſaluation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that walk before him in truth, though we haue no preſent ſight or feeling either of the one, or of the other. For we muſt conſider the conſtant truth of Gods word, both in his iuſtice and mercie, which in time ſhall be verified, though for the preſent there be no viſible ſignes and tokens thereof to be ſeene or felt of our ſelues, or any other.</p>
            <p>The third example is of Sarah the mother of vs all: of whome it is ſaid,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14254:60"/> that through faith ſhee receiued ſtrength to conceiue ſeede,<note place="margin">verſ. 11.</note> and was deliuered of a child, when ſhee was paſt age, becauſe ſhee iudged him faithfull which had promiſed. When a man child was firſt promiſed vnto her, beeing both old and barren; as long as ſhe meaſured things by ſight and feeling, ſhee beleeued not this, neither could:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 18.11.</note> For ſhee ſaw, that it ceaſed to be with her after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of women, therefore ſhee laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at it within her ſelfe, as at a thing impoſſible: for which ſhee was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued with theſe words, Shall any thing be hard to the Lord? But when ſhee gaue ouer conſulting with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhee beleeued not onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but cleane contrarie to all ſenſe and feeling: for ſhee looked onely to this, that he was iuſt and true, who had promiſed it vnto her: and by this faith was made fruitfull. So in matters of faith we muſt not looke
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14254:60"/> what we ſee and feele in our ſelues, or in any meanes to effect them; but what God hath promiſed, and how faithfull he is to performe.</p>
            <p>And ſo did Abraham, of whome it is written,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.5.</note> that the Lord brought him forth, and ſaide, Looke vp now to heauen, and tell the ſtarres, if thou be able to number them: and he ſaid vnto him, So ſhall thy ſeede be: and Abraham beleeued the Lord. And the Apoſtle commendeth this faith in him ſo much the more, becauſe he conſidered not his own body,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.1</note> which was now dead; (that is, voide of ſtrength and vigour to get children) beeing almoſt an hundred yeare old: neither the deadnes of Saras wombe, who was both aged, and barren. Both which if he had looked vnto, he could haue had no ſight or feeling of that, that was promiſed: for they were directly againſt it. But he gaue this glorie to God,<note place="margin">verſ. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that he was fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14254:61"/> that he that had promiſed it, was able to doe it: and ſo aboue hope, he beleeued vnder hope, that he ſhould be the father of many nations, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which was ſpoken vnto him, So ſhall thy ſeede be. And ſo he beleeued that, which he neither had, nor could haue any preſent ſight, or feeling of.</p>
            <p>Thus both Abraham and Sarah beleeued that, which they could haue no feeling of in themſelues: and ſo muſt all the ſonnes of Abraham, and daughters of Sarah. And thus to doe is not onely faith, but the greateſt faith. For if they could haue ſeen how this might haue beene done: and haue felt ſuch ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in their bodies, that they might perceiue it very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the courſe of nature; then it had beene no great matter to beleeue it: nay it had beene great infidelitie not to beleeue it. So for vs to beleeue the promiſes of God, when we may ſee
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14254:61"/> and feele, how they may be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that is a matter of no moment: but when all things go againſt them, &amp; we haue no ſight or feeling at all in our ſelues, of that that is ſaid vnto vs: then to beleeue God, and to giue this glory vnto him, that he is able to performe it, is a matter of great faith. And therefore here it is ſaid of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, not onely that he beleeued, but that he was not weake in faith:<note place="margin">verſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that is, very ſtrong and conſtant in faith. So that the Spirit of God commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this in him, as an high degree of faith, that he beleeued without ſight or feeling: to ſhew vs that faith is ſo many times ſeuered from fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that it is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrongeſt, when we conſtantly beleeue that, which we neither ſee, nor feele, but waite vpon God for them both.</p>
            <p>And this is that, which was in our Sauiour Chriſt alſo: who though he did alwaies put his truſt in his father,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14254:62"/> and was ſure that he loued him: and his faith this way was as pretious and pure as gold: yet it did moſt of all ſhew it ſelfe in his full ſtrength, when he came to ſuffer vpon the croſſe: when it was ſo many waies aſſaulted, that contrary to all ſenſe and feeling he remained conſtant, and ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came: to ſuccour all thoſe, that ſhall be oppreſſed with the temptations of vnbeleefe, becauſe they haue no feeling. For when things did lie ſo heauie vpon him, he beeing then to beare all our ſinnes and corruptions, and in them to appeare before God his father, and to anſwer for them; yea, to ſatisfie his wrath by induring the full puniſhment of them: firſt of all it is written of him, that he began to waxe ſorowfull,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 26.37.</note> and grieuouſly troubled in his minde: and this griefe was ſo deadly, that he was not able to containe it in himſelfe, but did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray it with moſt lamentable words
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14254:62"/> vnto his Diſciples, that he might haue comfort from them; ſaying,<note place="margin">verſ. 38.</note> My ſoule is very heauie vnto the death, tarie ye here, and watch with me: and then becauſe his grief was not aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged;<note place="margin">39.</note> he fell vpon his face downe to the ground, and praied, ſaying, O my father, if it be poſſible, let this cuppe paſſe from me. And thus he praied the ſecond and third time. And that it might appeare, what vncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtriuing he had in himſelfe all this while, not onely with death; but with the fearefull iudgement of his angrie father; it is further added, that he fell into a great agonie,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and diſtraction of minde, whereby all his bodie was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered, ſo that for anguiſh his ſweate was like drops of blood trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe to the cold ground.</p>
            <p>And at the laſt when he was vpon the croſſe, he was further aſſaulted with temptations from the ſpeeches of men, euen his enemies, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiled
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14254:63"/> him,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath. 27.39.</note> wagging their heads, and caſting out many opprobrious ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt him,<note place="margin">40.</note> ſaying, If thou be the ſonne of God, come downe from the croſſe: he truſted in God, let him deliuer him, if he will haue him: for he ſaide, I am the ſonne of God. Whereby his diſcomforts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements for our ſakes, were ſo increaſed, that at the laſt he braſt forth into theſe moſt lamentable words,<note place="margin">46.</note> and as the Euangeliſt ſaith, ſtraining as it were all the parts of his bodie, and powers of his ſpirit, hee cried with a loud voice; My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? All this while what preſent ſight and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling could he haue of Gods fauour? when as not onely all things out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly did ſhew, but his words alſo did abundantly declare, that inwardly he felt the contrarie.</p>
            <p>Therefore his faith was now the greateſt, as it was meete it ſhould be,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14254:63"/> to incounter and ouercome ſo many and great temptations: when as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to all theſe things, which he ſaw and felt, he not only praied moſt earneſtly vnto his father, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued therein, praying three times the ſame words, with ſuch feruencie of ſpirit, that beeing vpon the cold ground, he ſweat water and blood: and he praied in faith;<note place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note> For when he did offer vp thoſe praiers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations with ſtrong crying and teares vnto him,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.4</note> that was able to ſaue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, he was heard in the thing which he feared; and God ſent an Angel vnto him from heauen to comfort him. Whereby he came to this reſolution of minde, that he qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly ſubmitted himſelfe in theſe his ſufferings vnto the will of his father; ſaying, Abba, father,<note place="margin">Mark. 14.</note> all things are poſſible vnto thee: take away this cup from me: neuertheleſſe, not that I will, but that thou wilt be done. And
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14254:64"/> beeing now at the point of death, &amp; in the middeſt of all his ſufferings, and in the height of his temptations, that it might appeare that he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome all,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k. 23.46.</note> he cried out with a loud voice, ſtraining himſelfe to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, when life was almoſt out of his weake and painfull bodie, Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thine hands I commend my ſpirit; and when he thus had ſaide, he gaue vp the ghoſt, &amp; quietly died. Which wordes of his beeing vttered with great zeale, did ſhew the excellencie and perfection of his faith; eſpecially if we conſider in what caſe he was then: and ſo his faith was the greateſt, when he had the leaſt feeling.</p>
            <p>And thus no doubt the ſeruants of God in their ſeuerall afflictions of body and mind, and otherwiſe are in meaſure made like vnto Chriſt: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as hauing nothing, that by any ſight or feeling, inward or outward, might miniſter vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14254:64"/> and therefore in ſuch caſes they are greatly diſcouraged and caſt downe in themſelues; yet they holde out conſtantly in them to the end: then the more like they are vnto Chriſt in his ſufferings, the more like ſhall they be vnto him in his glory. For then is their faith the greateſt, when in this forlone eſtate of theirs (as it may ſeeme) they can pray vnto God as Chriſt did, and ſeeke for all helpe and comfort from him: and neuer leaue praying till God heare them, as Chriſt continued in his prayer, till an Angel was ſent vnto him. And in the meane time whatſoeuer becomes of them, they with a quiet and meeke ſpirit reſigne vp themſelues wholly to his bleſſed will, being contented whatſoeuer they deſire, that not their owne, but Gods will may take place: as Chriſt did, when he ſaid, Father not mine, but thy will be done.</p>
            <p>And if they doe ſo, that that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14254:65"/> preſent, of what nature and kind ſoeuer, ſhall make an end of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they can quietly and peaceably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend their ſoules and bodies, euen themſelues wholly liuing and dying into his bleſſed hands; as Chriſt did alſo vpon the croſſe, when he was readie to giue vp the ghoſt: beeing perſwaded, that nothing euer peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that was commited vnto his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie: according as he ſaith himſelfe, Thoſe that thou gaueſt me,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 17.12.</note> haue I kept, and none of them is loſt, but the child of perdition; that the Scripture might be fulfilled. If we can thus doe, though all this while we haue no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any preſent comfort, yet it may be truly ſaid vnto vs as it was to the woman of Canaan, who with many diſcouragements, and without all ſight or feeling of any fauour fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, purſued our Sauiour Chriſt with her prayers, and would not giue ouer, or take any repulſe, O woman,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14254:65"/> great is thy faith: and, O man,<note place="margin">Math. 15.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> great is thy faith, that doeſt thus, whoſoeuer thou art.</p>
            <p>And we haue a worthy example of the truth of this in one of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, of our owne country, and in the memory of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it is largely ſet out by M. Foxe in his laborious worke of the Acts and Monuments of the Church. The effect of which ſtorie ſhortly is this: M. Robert Glouer of Couentry gentl. and Maſter of Artes in Cambridge, was in the raigne of Q. Mary, with many the ſeruants of God by the malicious practiſes of the Papiſts apprehended, &amp; brought before the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe for his faith and religion, and after exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination he was ſent to priſon: where he receiued great comfort from the Lord from time to time; &amp; as his afflictions did increaſe, ſo did the comforts of the Lord abound; till at the laſt by the permiſſion of God,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14254:66"/> for his further triall and comfort, the Deuill did greatly aſſault him in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by the conſideration of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines to be counted in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, that ſhould ſuffer for Chriſts ſake: which temptation of the enemie, though he did conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſt at the firſt; yet after that he was condemned to death by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and was at the point to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered out of this world, it ſo happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that two or three daies before the time of his burning, his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lumpiſh, and deſtitute of all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall conſolation, and feeling of gods fauour, he felt in himſelfe no aptnes or willingnes, but rather an heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and dulnes of ſpirit, full of much diſcomfort to beare that bitter croſſe of Martyrdome, readie now to be laid vpon him.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he fearing himſelfe, leaſt the Lord had vtterly withdrawn his woonted fauour from him, made
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14254:66"/> his moane to one M. Auſten Bernher a miniſter, &amp; a familiar friend of his: ſignifying vnto him, how earneſtly he had praied day and night vnto the Lord, and yet could receiue no motion, nor ſenſe of any comfort from him. Vnto whome the ſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten anſwering againe, willed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him patiently to wait the Lords pleaſure, and howſoeuer his preſent feeling was, yet ſeeing his cauſe was iuſt and true, he exhorted him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to ſticke to the ſame, and play the man: nothing miſdoubting, but the Lord in time would viſit him, and ſatisfie his deſire with plentie of conſolation. Whereof (he ſaide) he was right certen and ſure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired him, whenſoeuer any ſuch feeling of Gods heauenly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſhould begin to touch his heart, that then he would ſhew ſome ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication thereof, whereby he might witneſſe with him the ſame: and ſo
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14254:67"/> departed from him.</p>
            <p>The next day, when the time came of his martyrdome, as he was going to the place, and was now come to the ſight of the ſtake: although all the night before praying earneſtly to God for ſtrength and courage, hee could finde none, neither had any ſight or taſte of the fauour of God in himſelfe, ſodenly he was ſo mightily repleniſhed with Gods holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, &amp; heauenly ioyes, that he could not ſmother it in himſelfe, but cried out clapping his hands to Auſten, and ſaying on this wiſe, Auſten, he is come, he is come, &amp;c. and that with ſuch ioy and alacritie, as one ſeeming rather to be riſen from ſome deadly daunger, to libertie of life, then one paſſing out of this world by any pains of death. Here we ſee that great was his faith, when he was willing to giue his bodie to be burnt for the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Chriſt, and was now going to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14254:67"/> the ſtake to that ende, though he had no feeling of Gods fauour then by any ioyes that he felt in himſelfe. He could neuer haue ſuffered thus for the truth, if he had no faith: if then he had died in this caſe without the ſenſe of any ſpeciall comfort, he muſt needs haue died in the faith of Chriſt for which he did ſuffer: and ſo hee ſhould haue had faith, yea very great faith, not onely liuing, but dying without any ſenſe or feeling.</p>
            <p>But I will come vnto an other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which though it be far more ancient in time, yet is better knowne vnto vs, as being recorded in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture. The patience of Iob as it is ſet downe as a patterne, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to all men to follow, ſo none can doubt of his faith alſo, but that it was very great: When he is thus nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among the faithfulleſt men that haue liued vpon the face of the earth. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land ſinneth againſt me by
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14254:68"/> committing a treſpaſe,<note place="margin">Ezec. 14.13.</note> then will I ſtrech out mine hand vpon it, and though theſe three men, Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, and Iob were among them, they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe; ſaith the Lord God. When all that miſery came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, that we read of in the Scripture: as that in one day he loſt ſeauen thouſand ſheepe,<note place="margin">Iob 1.3.</note> three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand camels, fiue hundred yoake of oxen, fiue hundred ſhee aſſes: and all his ſonnes and daughters died a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death after a ſtrange manner; and in his owne bodie he was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with ſore boiles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſole of his foote, vnto the crowne of his head. And he beeing in this pitifull caſe, all friends did forſake him; yea they tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were younger then he did mocke him,<note place="margin">ch. 30 1.</note> and they whoſe fathers he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſet with the dogs of his flockes And his men ſeruants &amp; maids tooke him as a ſtraunger,<note place="margin">ch. 10. 16.</note> and though h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:14254:68"/> called them, they would not anſwer him; though he prayed them with his mouth: &amp; his breath was ſtrange vnto his wife, though he prayed her for the childrens ſake of her owne body. And three of his pricipall friends did ſet themſelues againſt him, &amp; by their reaſoning did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourage him, as though he had beene an hypocrite all the daies of his life, and that his holines of life was but in ſhew, and not in truth. And he had no reſt neither night nor day, for when he laid himſelfe down, he ſaide, When ſhall I ariſe:<note place="margin">ch. 7.4.</note> and ſo meaſuring the euening, he was weary with toſſing too &amp; fro, vnto the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day. Neither was he quiet waking nor ſleeping: for when he ſaid, my couch ſhall releeue me,<note place="margin">13.</note> and my bed ſhall bring comfort in my meditation, the lord feared him with dreames, and aſtonied him with viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:14254:69"/>
            <p>Now when all theſe things came vpon him at once, whereby his eſtate was more miſerable, then I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, or you are able to conceiue, what ſenſe and feeling could he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly haue of Gods fauour, either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or outward, when all things thus went againſt him? yet now his faith was at the higheſt, and did ſhew it ſelfe in the greateſt meaſure, when he vttered this moſt excellent ſaying, Loe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.15.</note> though he kill me, yet will I truſt in him. So that he would not giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his truſt and confidence in Gods goodnes, though he ſhould proceed further againſt him vnto death. And moſt of all when he further addeth, I am ſure,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k 19.25.</note> that my Redeemer liueth, and he ſhal ſtand the laſt on the earth; and though after my skinne wormes deſtroy this bodie, yet I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh: whome I my ſelfe ſhall ſee, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and none other for me, though my raines
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14254:69"/> are conſumed within me. So that though he died in that caſe without all outward comfort, or inward fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, yet hee would put his truſt in God: hauing the teſtimony of a good conſcience, and relying vpon the promiſe of God made concerning the reſurrection of his bodie, and life euerlaſting in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Thus then we ought to be ſo farre from beeing diſcouraged in our ſelues for want of the ſight and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of inward comforts, as though therefore wee had no faith; as that when they ſhall be altogether taken from vs for a while, though very long, and many yeares: yet if we can then hold out in a godly life, and not giue ouer a good conſcience, as Iob did; and if we ſtill call vpon the name of God, and ſtay vpon his promiſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n life and death, though we doe not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et inioy them: all the world ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen witneſſe for vs, that our faith is
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14254:70"/> exceeding great, though wee our ſelues be not able to ſee it, neither can be perſwaded of it. For as when the ſunne ſhineth moſt clearely, and men doe ſee the brightnes of it, and doe feele the ſcortching heate of it, then it is an eaſie matter to beleeue, and to ſay confidently, there is a ſunne in the firmament: euen children and thoſe that are of meane capacitie, are able to ſay ſo, and doe beleeue as much, and haue ſuch a full perſwaſion of it, that if all the world ſhould tell them the contrary, they would not beleeue them, neither could they poſſibly doubt of it, their ſight &amp; feeling did ſufficiently inſtruct them. But when the cloudes ſhall couer it, or in the night both the light and heat thereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be taken away; then to be full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſwaded, that the ſunne is ſtill i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the heauens, and that it hath loſt no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing of the light and heate of it; tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is a matter of a deeper conceit, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:14254:70"/> more experience.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo when the teſtimonies of Gods fauour and loue are ſo many &amp; great, and ſo plentifully vpon vs, both outwardly and inwardly, that they may eaſily be ſeene and felt; then to beleeue, that God is gratious vnto vs, and to be perſwaded of his fauour towards vs, is that which the weakeſt in faith may attaine vnto without any difficultie: But when all theſe ſhall be taken away, not onely in our owne iudgement, but in the opinion alſo of others, and the light of Gods cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſhall be, as it were, darkned with the cloudes of aduerſitie, and all things outwardly ſhall be as vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable vnto vs, as the darkeſt night of winter; yet then to beleeue, that God is one and the ſame towards vs, and that his loue ſuffereth no eclypſe at all, but is the ſame ſtill to vs, and to all thoſe that are his, becauſe whome be once loueth, he loueth vnto the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14254:71"/> ende,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 11.29.</note> and that the gifts and calling of God are without repentance: &amp; that all the paths of the Lord are mercie and truth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 25.50.</note> vnto thoſe that keepe his couenant, and his teſtimonies; that is, that he is not onely mercifull vnto them in the beginning, but alſo true and conſtant in his mercies towards all his euen vnto the ending, to finiſh and make perfect in them that good worke of his, that he hath begunne in them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 15.29.</note> For he is not like vnto man that hee ſhould repent him of any thing, that he hath done: and as S. Iames ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 1.19.</note> with him there is no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riablenes, or ſhadow of turning. To be, I ſay, thus perſwaded, when theſe things ſhall be vpon vs, and ſo to reſt in the truth of Gods promiſes, and to waite patiently for a comfortable fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the performance of them in our ſelues, is a matter of greater faith, and of longer experience.</p>
            <p>Againe, as if a man doth come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14254:71"/> a fruitfull garden or orchyard, well ſet with many trees in the ſpring time, when all things are greene and bloſſome, or in ſommer, when the trees are full of fruit; it is the eaſieſt thing in the world then euen at the firſt ſight to be perſwaded, that the trees are liuing and growing: and he that hath the weakeſt ſenſes, &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt wit, and leaſt experience, is able to ſay ſo: But to come thether in the depth of winter, when all the fruit ſhall be gathered, and the leaues fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and ſee all the bowes, white with the whore froſt, and rine hanging vpon euery twigge, ſo that outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſeeme to be dead and rotten; yet then to be perſwaded, that they are liuing, and that the ſappe is at the roote, which in time will come into all the branches againe, and ſhew it ſelf, as before, in putting forth leaues, bloſſomes, and fruit: this requireth better iudgement, &amp; more experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:14254:72"/>
            <p>So is it in the matter of faith: when all the teſtimonies of Gods loue doe aboundantly ſhew themſelues, as it were in ſomer, it is an eaſie matter to beleeue: but when all theſe ſhall be fallen away from vs, as they were fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iob;</hi> and there is a very hard &amp; long winter ful of many ſtormes come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; yet then not to be too much diſcouraged &amp; caſt downe, as though all were cleane loſt and gone: but to be perſwaded, that the fauour of God is not cleane dried vp, but is at the roote, that is, is the ſame in Chriſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, that euer it was; and that, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 13.6.</note> Ieſus Chriſt is ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, and to day, and will be the ſame for euer: and that the light of Gods countenance is not cleane put out, but darkned, and couered with a vaile for a time: and ſo with a quiet and meeke ſpirit to waite vpon God in all well doing, till there be a new ſpring, and till the ſunne breake out
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14254:72"/> of the clouds againe. Thus to doe, is that great faith, that ſhal vphold vs in all extremities. And as in theſe caſes we would condemne others of want of wiſdome, which would beleeue no more then they ſaw or felt: ſo muſt we condemne our ſelues and others of want of ſpirituall and heauenly wiſdome of the word of God, that in ſuch caſes as theſe of our ſaluation, we will beleeue no more, then we can ſee and feele: and we muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the other to be of better iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and greater faith, who doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue more then they could either ſee or feele.</p>
            <p>For the releeuing of our ſelues therefore in ſuch caſes as theſe, what muſt wee doe? Wee muſt doe that, which Thomas the Apoſtle ſhould haue done: namely, he ſhould haue beleeued thoſe that tolde him, that Chriſt was riſen, and that they had ſeene him: and he ſhould haue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14254:73"/> the wordes of Chriſt himſelfe, who had foretold him, that he ſhould be put to death, and that within three daies he ſhould riſe againe: which wordes of Chriſt muſt needes haue beene verified in their time, though none had euer ſeene him. So muſt we doe, euen beleeue the word and promiſes of God, in the mouthes of his faithfull ſeruants, who are able both to ſee further into them, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to diſcerne more teſtimonies of faith, and of the fauour of God in vs, then we our ſelues can doe. And though we, whome they doe moſt of all concerne, doe not ſee them at all, or as we deſire: it is ſufficient, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom we ought to credit, doe ſee them in vs, and do conſtantly and vpon their credit auouch the ſame vnto vs.</p>
            <p>For it is moſt certaine and true, though eury man ſhould beſt knowe himſelfe: yet it ſo often falleth out,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14254:73"/> that wee are not fit iudges of our ſelues, and of our own eſtate, neither of body, nor of ſoule: and therefore if we will be rightly perſwaded of our ſelues, we muſt not ſo much rely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our owne iudgement, as giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vnto others; which may and doe ſee that in vs, which wee our ſelues doe not, neither can. As when a man is daungerouſly ſicke of ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, though he haue ſome generall knowledge of the eſtate of his body, yet he may take himſelfe to be ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or weaker, nearer or further off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, then indeed he is: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch caſe we ask the aduiſe of ſome skilfull Phyſitians, and truſt their iudgement better then our owne; in ſo much that though a man be a very skilfull Phyſitian, he will hardly or not at all practiſe vpon him ſelfe in great extremities, but vſeth the helpe of other Phyſitians, and is contented to be ordered at their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion:
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:14254:74"/> Euen ſo when a man is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ſicke in his ſoule, either of vnbeleefe, or otherwiſe, he is not to iudge of himſelf at that time, though he be a very good chriſtian, but he muſt for his recouerie out of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, vſe the helpe of other godly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and hearken vnto their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And that we might ſee the truth of this moſt clearly in an other caſe, we muſt conſider, that as when the Deuill preuaileth againſt vs by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, we ſo fauour our ſelues, &amp; are ſo partiall that way, that we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, both that we haue thoſe vertues and graces of God in vs, and that in great meaſure, which we haue not, neither can any man ſee them in vs; and alſo that we are free from thoſe corruptions and ſinnes, which yet do apparantly breake out in vs, and all the world may eaſily ſee them: So on the otherſide, when he hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:14254:74"/> the aduantage of vs by diffidence &amp; deſpaire, he maketh vs to rigorous &amp; hard againſt our ſelues; and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs that we want thoſe graces, which doe apparantly ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to others; and to haue thoſe ſinnes &amp; corruptions, and that meaſure of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which in truth we haue not, neither is any able to diſcerne them in vs, though we crie out againſt our ſelues for them.</p>
            <p>So that in both theſe eſtates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we deceiue our ſelues of our ſelues, if we wilbe holpen, we muſt deny our ſelues, and not meaſure our ſelues by our ſelues, but giue credit to thoſe, who as they are wiſe to diſcerne, and faithfull to iudge; ſo are they alſo true to report what they thinke of vs, and of our eſtate. Which if we will not doe, we muſt needes continue in our vnbeleefe, and other ſinnes ſo much the longer: and it ſhall be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard thing to recouer vs out of the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14254:75"/> ſame. Let vs therefore as we loue our owne good, in ſuch extreame caſes as theſe, when by the temptation of Satan we are brought to a narrowe poynt, hearken vnto thoſe faithfull miniſters and godly brethren of ours, who are able, (becauſe they are out of temptation, and the caſe is not their owne) better to iudge of vs, then we our ſelues: and then haue we made a good entrance vnto the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our ſoules, though we be not preſently reſtored to perfect health: and though we haue not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent comfort, yet the extremities of our feares ſhall be greatly ſtaied: and this ſtaying of vs wil miniſter further hope of full recouerie: and it is none of the leaſt mercies of God to ſee, that we haue beene deceiued in our ſelues, and are not able rightly to iudge of our ſelues. Thus we ſee, how faith, and great faith, is without fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: and when we be oppreſſed with
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:14254:75"/> this temptation, how we muſt helpe our ſelues by beleeuing others more then our ſelues, yea euen of our owne ſelues.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, to this effect muſt we be admoniſhed, that as in the natural life there are three ages, the infancie, the childhood or youth, and the riper and perfect age: ſo in the ſpirituall life the Scripture maketh mention of three ages; for of thoſe that are in Chriſt, and truly belong vnto him, ſome are new borne babes,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> as S. Peter calleth them, but newly begotten of the immortall ſeede of the word of God: others are little children,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.19</note> that haue more profited in knowledge, and in the myſterie of their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſome are in compariſon of them, perfect men,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and are comming vnto the meaſure of their full age in Chriſt. Theſe latter are able to iudge of themſelues, and of others: for by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong cuſtome they haue their wits<note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:14254:76"/> exerciſed to diſcerne both good and euill: the ſecond ſort, is leſſe able to iudge of themſelues, the third not at all. A babe though it be heire appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant vnto the crowne of the greateſt Monarch in the world, it hath no ſenſe or feeling of it: nay, though it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, it is not able to iudge of it ſelfe, whether it hath life or no: but others doe ſee by the operations of life, that it is a liuing creature, and hath an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſoule: and dying in that eſtate, yea as ſoone as it is borne, it ſhall her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after liue for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>So a great many, that are borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of water,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3 5.</note> and of the Spirit, and thereby are made heires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, as Chriſt ſaith to Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus; they are neuer but babes, beyond that age they neuer goe, and ſome of them fal aſleepe in the Lord, as ſoone as they are made partakers of this ſpirituall birth; as the theefe vpon the croſſe died preſently after
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14254:76"/> his conuerſion: and Chriſt ſheweth vs in the Goſpel, that ſome are called at the eleuenth houre to work in the vineyard, that is,<note place="margin">Math. 20.6.</note> in their later part of their life they are called to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate of ſaluation and grace, and to receiue the reward of their calling, which is eternall life. In which eſtate of theirs they can haue little or no feeling at all of their ſpirituall life. But as other children die before they know, that they were aliue; ſo theſe die before they did feele any great power of the ſpirituall life in themſelues. But as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did ſee that it was aliue, becauſe they ſaw how it deſired the milke of their mothers, &amp; how they did thriue by it: ſo others may ſee in ſuch ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall infants, that the life of God is in them by the appetite that they haue vnto the word of God, that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it, as their appointed food, as Iob ſaith of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Iob 23.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they grow in many graces of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14254:77"/> Spirit of God, as in a feare to offend him, and in a deſire vnto their owne ſaluation, though they haue little aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, ſenſe, or feeling of it in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelue and ſo are heires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God, though they die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euer they had any great feeling of it in themſelues.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe that are of riper age in Chriſt, and haue had ſome feeling of their ſaluation, and haue loſt it; they are not to be addicted to their owne iudgement, to thinke they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had it, becauſe it is now loſt, or that they ſhall neuer haue it againe, becauſe it is taken from them for a while; for the life of God may ſtill be in them, though the preſent feeling of it be taken away: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at this time, concerning their owne preſent ſtate, they muſt beleeue others, that can ſee more into them, then themſelues. For as in ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the bodie a man may haue all
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14254:77"/> his ſenſes taken away from him for a while; or he may be ſo ſore wounded in the head, and his braine ſo diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, that he can not tell, whether himſelfe be aliue or dead: but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs by their breathing, and ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> operations of life doe ſee euidently, that life remaineth in them, and ſo hope that they may be recouered. So a man may be ſo ſpiritually ſicke of vnbeleefe, or ſo ſore wounded in his ſoule with temptations, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee any token of Gods fauour in himſelfe; but yet by the praiers that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e maketh vnto God to be holpen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of theſe diſtreſſes, by the loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he beareth vnto God, and to Gods people, and other operations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the ſpirit of God in him, they that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re wiſe ſhall be able to diſcerne that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e life of Gods ſpirit breatheth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em, to whome they muſt giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it aboue themſelues: and ſo thinke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at they are in a better eſtate of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14254:78"/> then they can ſee themſelues to be.</p>
            <p>And it muſt not ſeeme ſtraunge vnto vs, that other ſhould ſee better into our eſtate, then we our ſelues can. For oftentimes it falleth out, that ſome great affection of the minde ſo blindeth vs, that we imagine that we haue not that, which indeed we haue. He that is blinded with couetouſnes of theſe worldly goods, by the vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable deſire that is in him, neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, though he hath more to liu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on then many hundreds, yet ſtill h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is complaining of his want, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty; and ſaith, that he hath nothing and tel him of this, and of that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God hath beſtowed vpon him, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> becauſe he hath not all that he deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth, he maketh no account of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and all is vnto him, as though he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> nothing. So he that is ſicke of a ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall couetouſneſſe, and deſireth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feeling of Gods fauour in a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:14254:78"/> me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and ſuch an aſſurance of his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, as might be without al doubt: which becauſe he can not come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, becauſe the fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and in it there is nothing but doubting, he imagineth that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is ſome want of aſſurance and feeling, that therefore there is no feeling at all: as the couetous man by reaſon of ſome want, ſaith that he hath nothing: the want of that, which he hath not, ſo blindeth his eyes, that he can not ſee that, that he hath: ſo the want of ſome aſſurance ſo troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, and they haue ſo great a deſire vnto more, that they can not ſee that they haue, but for want of ſome, denie all.</p>
            <p>A remedie againſt which tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, not to deceiue our ſelues any longer with an imagination of ſuch a meaſure of aſſurance of ſaluation ordinarily in the children of God, which ſhould be without all waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14254:79"/> or doubting: or ſuch a meaſure of feeling of the loue of God, and ioy therein, as ſhould abandon all diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtfulnes and ſorow: this is not to be looked for in this world:<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> the fulneſſe of ioy is in the preſence of God, and at his right hand onely are pleaſures for euermore: here we haue them but in meaſure: there indeede is ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, and moſt glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all interruption; when we ſhall ſee God face to face:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> and know him as we are knowne, whome now we behold as through a glaſſe, and ſo may ſometimes doubt, whether we ſee him or no. This meaſure we muſt be contented with, and ſo pray as the Pſalmiſt doth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.4, 5.</note> Remember me, O Lord, with the fauour of thy people, that I may ſee the felicity of thy cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: where he deſireth not ſuch ioy &amp; feeling of the fauour of god, which he did imagine himſelfe, but which God doth vſually beſtow vpon his
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14254:79"/> people, which is that that is ioyned with much doubting, &amp; many feares, euen then ſometimes when it is at the beſt: and ſo not imagine, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wee haue it according to our owne deſire, we haue it not at all, or as Gods people vſe to haue it. For vndoubtedly it is thus with the beſt, at one time or other.</p>
            <p>And concerning this deſire of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and aſſurance, wee muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thus much, that none can haue this, but thoſe that beleeue: ſo that though we ſhould want them both altogether, yet the deſire that wee haue vnto them, doth manifeſtly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue that we haue faith. For who can deſire to feele the heate and light of the ſunne, but he that hath life in him? a dead carkaſe cannot doe it. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f there were not the life of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it in vs by faith, we could not haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y deſire to feele the fauour of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n vs in truth at all. He that is neuer
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14254:80"/> ſo weake, yet if he ſtill deſire ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, it appeareth that there is life in him: ſo when we moſt earneſtly deſire to be ſtrengthened in the aſſurance of our ſaluation, it is a manifeſt token, that the life of God is ſtill in vs: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs comfort our ſelues with ſuch deſires, and know aſſuredly, that as they be of God, ſo he will ſatisfie them in his good time: for the Lord heareth the deſire of the poore,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17.</note> he prepareth their heart, and bendeth his eare vnto them: that is, as he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them ſo earneſtly to deſire theſe things, which others neglect, ſo he will ſhew by giuing alſo that which they doe deſire, that he hath not giuen them ſuch holy deſires in vaine. For the ſaying of our Sauiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt muſt be verified vpon all men without reſpect of perſons,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.6.</note> Bleſſed are all they that hunger and thirſt, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely after righteouſnes, but after a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other graces of his Spirit, for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:14254:80"/> ſhall be ſatisfied and filled. And the ſaying of the virgine Marie ſhall be verified in them,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.53.</note> He hath filled the hungrie with good things, and ſent away the rich emptie: that is, as they that haue no ſuch deſires, can looke for no ſuch feeling, ſo they that are vnſatiable in their deſires that way, ſhall be ſatisfied in time with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of feeling: and if they waite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God with patience, beleeuing theſe promiſes, it ſhall be vnto them according to their faith.</p>
            <p>That I might not ſay here that, which is yet moſt true, that while they ſo vnmeaſurably deſire it, they haue it in a good meaſure. For here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the ſaying of S. Auguſtine moſt true, that the deſire of any grace of God, is in ſome ſort the grace it ſelfe. He that vnfainedly deſireth the forgiuenes of his ſinnes, doth with this deſire obtaine the remiſſion of them. He that deſireth a greater
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:14254:81"/> meaſure of repentance, doth from day to day profit in repentance: he that deſireth not to ſinne, is no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner before God: he that deſireth the fauour of God, hath obtained it alreadie: he that deſireth the aſſurance of his ſaluation, and the feeling of Gods fauour, he hath both of them in ſome ſort already. When Abraham was willing to offer vp his ſonne Izack at Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.17.</note> he is ſaid to haue don it by faith: his deſire before god, was as though he had done it: ſo when we offer vp theſe deſires vnto God, it is as well with vs in his account, as though we had the things themſelues.</p>
            <p>For as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> almes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 8.12.</note> if there be firſt a willing min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is accepted according to that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath, and not according to that tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a man hath not: that is, God looketh not ſo much to his deede, as to his deſire: as the poore widow that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14254:81"/> but two mites, was more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, and commended by Chriſt, then they that offered much, becauſe of her great deſire. So when in the ſacrifice of prayer we offer vp our hearts vnto god with holy deſires either for aſſurance of his fauour, or feeling of our ſaluation, we are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him, as though we had them: and when he giueth vs this deſire, he beginneth to worke the grace it ſelfe: and that deſire is the earneſt peny &amp; pledge of the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaith in the Goſpel, that whoſoeuer looketh on a woman to luſt after her,<note place="margin">Math. 5.2</note> hath committed adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with her already in his heart. So that the deſire vnto any ſin, is the ſin it ſelfe before God: then the deſire vnto any vertue, is the vertue and grace it ſelfe before God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that looketh vp vnto God with an earneſt deſire of his ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he hath obtained it alreadie before
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:14254:82"/> God, who ſeeth &amp; aloweth the deſire of his heart. He that looketh on his own vnbeleefe and corruptions with a deſire to be rid of them, he is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcharged of them before God. Thus we ſee, that to deſire feeling is an argument of faith, as to deſire meate is an argument of life: yea to deſire feeling, is the very beginning of it in our ſelues: and therefore we muſt be comforted ouer them.</p>
            <p>Concerning which feelings, we muſt alſo conſider, that in them that haue them in the greateſt meaſure, they are not alwaies alike: but they are going and comming, as the day and the night. And as in the courſe of nature there is not one tenour of things, but Gods works are ſubiect to many changes: ſo is it in the courſe of Gods grace: that which we haue receiued, doth not alwaies continue alike, neither haue we the ſame fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it to day, that we had yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day:
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14254:82"/> whether we looke to the feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of prayer, or zeale to Gods word, or loue to his Saints, or aſſurance of our ſaluation. Here we muſt comfort our ſelues with the remembrance of that that we haue found in our ſelues in times paſt, and hope that we may finde the like againe: and ſay as it is in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.1 &amp; 119.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I haue remembred the times paſt, and haue beene comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For as the woman that is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with child, and feeleth it ſtirre in her bodie, though ſhee doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies feele it ſtirre alike; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not at all, and ſometimes more weakely then before: yet ſhee aſſures her ſelfe, that the child is liuing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee hath felt it ſtirre before, &amp; ſo hopeth that ſhee ſhall doe againe. So when Chriſt is formed in vs firſt of all, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.1</note> we haue the feeling of him ſtirring and moouing in our hearts by his holy Spirit, dwelling in vs: which liuely
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14254:83"/> motions though wee feele not ſo ſtrongly moouing in vs afterwards, or not at all; yet we doubt not, but that Chriſt dwelleth in our hearts by faith ſtill,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> and hope to feele it as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly againe in time, as we haue done: &amp; ſo much the more, becauſe Chriſt beeing formed in vs, neuer dieth: and therefore the remembrance of our former Feelings muſt comfort vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the want of them for the time preſent: for they are not alwaies alike in any that haue them: it is ſufficient that we haue had them, therefore if we labour after them, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto vs againe, when it ſhall pleaſe God. And thus much for this, that S. <hi>Thomas</hi> in this matter of faith addicts himſelfe to his owne feeling.</p>
            <p>THe fourth and laſt degree of his vnbeleefe appeareth in this, Except I ſee in his hands the print of the nayles, and in his ſide the print of the ſpeare, I will not beleeue it. For
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14254:83"/> why ſhould he deſire this? not onely to ſee him, and to feele him; but to ſee in his hands the print of the nailes, and to put his finger into them; and to ſee in his ſide the print of the ſpeare, and to put his hand into it. Did he not know that theſe wounds and skarres were proper vnto his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die onely while it was ſubiect vnto infirmitie and weaknes: and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection his bodie was glorified? And ſo he might haue thought, that though it ſhould be graunted vnto him to ſee him, yet he could not by any reaſon or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Scripture, haue hope to ſee him thus: &amp; yet he ſaith, Except I ſee the print of the nailes, &amp;c. I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it: he doth not ſay, except I ſee him: but, except I ſee him with the print of the nayles, and of the ſpeare, I will not beleeue it.</p>
            <p>This is then the nature of vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, that when it will not profit by
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14254:84"/> the ordinarie meanes, that God hath appointed for the confirming of faith; it deſireth ſuch things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is no warrant, either from reaſon, or from Scripture. As here S. Thomas neglecting what Chriſt had ſaide vnto him, that when he ſhould be put to death, within three daies he would riſe again: and that alſo which was tolde him by the Apoſtles, and diuers others, namely, that he was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againe, and had appeared vnto ſuch and ſuch: he ſaith, Except I ſee him my ſelfe, with the print of the nayles in his feete, and of the ſpeare in his ſide, I will not beleeue it. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which poynt; though Chriſt did riſe indeede out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre with theſe markes in his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified body, and did retaine them whiles he taried on the earth, that thereby it might more certainely be knowne, that the ſame body of his that was crucified, was raiſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine;
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14254:84"/> yet Thomas had no generall rule to leade him to thinke that it ſhould be ſo, but rather according to the common condition of the bodies of all the faithfull in the day of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſo to conceiue of the body of Chriſt raiſed vp. For that which is ſaid of the reſurrection of all the faithful, the members of Chriſts myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, muſt needes be much more true of him the head: for it belongeth to them onely by vertue of his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Now of them the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus to the Corinthians;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.42.</note> The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ſowne in corruption, and raiſed in incorruption: that is, with nothing tending thereunto as wounds doe: it is ſowne in diſhonor, hauing no glory nor beauty on it, as Chriſts body was moſt of all, when beſides that the life was gone out of it, and ſo it looked pale and wanne; it had alſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formites by the ſtripes of his whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, and the crowne of thornes, &amp;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14254:85"/> the print of the nailes in his hands &amp; feete, and of the ſpeare in ſide: it is raiſed in glory; that is, with all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; excellencie of beauty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any blemiſh at all: it is ſowne in weakenes, it is raiſed in power: and therefore without marks and tokens of weakenes &amp; infirmitie: for a body ſore wounded, euen vnto death, as Chriſts was, hath leſſe power in it, then it had before. Therefore ſeeing he deſired to ſee Chriſts body raiſed vp, he ſhould not haue deſired to ſee it thus, and with theſe markes.</p>
            <p>And for the further confirmation of this, we may remember what the Apoſtle ſaith touching the glorious ſtate of our bodies to be raiſed vp: Our conuerſation is in heauen,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 3.20.</note> from whence alſo we looke for the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: who ſhall chaunge our vile bodie, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bodie, according to the working,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14254:85"/> whereby he is able euen to ſubdue all things vnto himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: therefore as we ſhall be raiſed vp without skarres and marks of infirmity, which many haue in theſe daies of their pilgrimage: ſo he had no reaſon to thinke, but that Chriſts bodie ſhould be. Therefore though he would not beleeue, till he ſawe him, he could not looke to ſee him after this manner, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth.</p>
            <p>And though he did at the laſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare with theſe markes in his body both to the eleuen firſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vnto Thomas: yet it was not becauſe his bodie was properly, and of it owne nature then ſubiect vnto them, no more then it was to hunger, when he did eate with them:<note place="margin">Luk. 24.43.</note> but it was by a ſpeciall extraordinarie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>penſation; as when Angels that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o bodies, did appeare in the ſhape of men. Therefore this could not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooked for: and it was in reſpect of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14254:86"/> the ordinarie courſe of Gods dealing ſomewhat vnreaſonable, to tie the Lord vnto that for the ſtrengthening of his faith, and to ſay, Except I ſee the print of the nayles, and of the ſpeare, I wil not beleeue it: for others had ſeene him, and not ſeene him with theſe;<note place="margin">Ioh. 20.15.</note> as Marie Magdalen at the ſepulchre, where ſhee miſtooke him to be the gardener, or the keeper of that place, where Chriſt was buried in a garden:<note place="margin">Mark. 16.12.</note> and the two Diſciples in their iourney, as they were going to Emmaus. Therefore we muſt take heede, how we yeild to our vnbeleef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for it will make vs looke for and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſuch things at the hand of God for the confirming of our faith, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue no ground either from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, or from reaſon: though it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth God of his infinite goodnes to beare with men ſometimes this way and to yeild to them, either to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrengthening of their faith, or to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:14254:86"/> leauing of them without excuſe in their vnbeleefe. So that as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith of couetouſnes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> They that will be rich fall into tentation and ſnares, and into many fooliſh and noiſome luſts, which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction; So we may ſay of vnbeleefe, that it cauſeth men to deſire many fooliſh and vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable things, and ſuch as often tende to their owne hurt.</p>
            <p>Thus in the Goſpel our Sauiour Chriſt in the parable of the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and in his perſon noteth out the thoughts and deſires of vnbeleeuers here in this world: where he is broght in ſpeaking vnto Abraham after this manner; I pray thee father,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.27.</note> that thou wouldeſt ſend Lazarus vnto my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe (for I haue many brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that he may teſtifie vnto them, leaſt they alſo come into this place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus vnbeleeuers would haue dead men come from heauen, &amp; tell
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14254:87"/> them what is done there, and what in hell: but Chriſt ſheweth what anſwer Abraham gaue him for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">29.</note> They haue Moſes, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, let them heare them: as if he had ſaid, they doe ſufficiently declare the truth of theſe things, of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they may learne them, and ſo it is neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to haue any come from heauen to tell them, there are enough vpon the earth, that doe declare it daily: &amp; ſo doe the Apoſtles, and the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts now much more. But the rich man ſaide againe,<note place="margin">30.</note> Father Abraham, but if one come from the dead, they will amend their liues: which is as if he had ſaid, Though they doe heare daily out of the Scripture, what puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhment is in hell for the wicked, yet they doe not beleeue it, except ſome come from the dead, and tell them of it, and then they would.</p>
            <p>Thus fooliſh is vnbeleefe, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the certen teſtimonie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14254:87"/> and Apoſtles, which is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie meanes to reueale his will vnto vs, and to deſire that Angels or dead men might come from heauen, or from hell to ſpeake vnto them, and then they would beleeue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which in theſe daies is ſo extraordinary, that it is not to be looked for. But this is a ſhort and plaine anſwer for ſuch men ſet downe there from Abraham, who ſaid thus vnto him,<note place="margin">31.</note> If they heare not Moſes and the Prophets, neither will they be perſwaded, though one riſe from the dead againe. Where Chriſt ſheweth not only what are the means of knowing theſe things, euen the bookes of the Prophets and Apoſtles in which the will of God is perfectly ſet downe concerning all things, that are needefull for vs to know, and that the other is not to be deſired, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for. So if they had them, they would not profit by them, when as they neglect the other: but yet we ſee
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:14254:88"/> by this, that vnbeleefe is full of theſe fooliſh deſires.</p>
            <p>And truly if we could ſo well ſee into the hearts of men, as Chriſt did when he vttered this parable, wee ſhould ſee, that the greateſt part of the world is ſtill of this mind, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect all the ordinarie meanes, that God hath appointed either to worke faith in them at the firſt, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it in them afterwards; and to deſire ſuch meanes, as are impoſſible and not to be looked for, becauſe they are contrarie to the word of God. For the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob. 1.1.</note> At ſundrie times, and in diuers manners God ſpake in the olde time to our fathers by the Prophets: but in theſe laſt daies he hath ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne: that is, in the old time. God did ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie waies declare his will vnto men, as ſometimes by viſions when they were waking, and by dreames when they were ſleeping, by Vrim &amp; Thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:14254:88"/> in the Prieſts breaſt, by Angels from heauen, by the Prophets, &amp;c. but now he hath fully declared his will by his ſonne Chriſt, and hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that we ſhould come to the knowledge of it by that order which Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed: who when he aſcended vp into heauen, gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church, Paſtors and teachers,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.12.</note> for the repairing of the Saints, for the worke of the miniſterie, and for the edification of the bodie of Chriſt, till we all meete together (in the vnitie of faith, and the acknowledging of the ſon of God) vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt: therefore as long as we liue, we are to looke for no other meanes then theſe of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and teachers, the other haue ceaſed long agoe, as beeing appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the old world.</p>
            <p>But yet vnbeleeuing men refuſe theſe, and with itching eares they
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14254:89"/> linger after the other: and ſome are ready to ſay, Oh if I might haue an Angel come and tell me of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that ſhall come vpon the wicked for their ſinne,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.13.</note> as Lot had in Sodom, I would beleeue it: and ſome are ready to ſay, if Lazarus might come from the dead, that is, if ſome of thoſe my freinds and aquaintance that are dead, might riſe out of their graues, and come and tell me, what they haue ſeene and felt in heauen &amp; hell, if I might haue but a litle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with them, I would beleeue them. Or if I could ſee into the heauens, and there behold Chriſt ſtanding at the right hand of God, as Stephen the Martyr did:<note place="margin">Act 7.56.</note> or if I could heare him ſpeake vnto me from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and call me from my ſinnes, as Saul did,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k 9.4.</note> when he was a perſecuter, then I would hearken vnto him, and become a new man. And others thinke, Oh if they might be rapt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:14254:89"/> the third heauens,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and be taken vp into paradiſe, as Paul was, and there heare God ſpeake vnto them, then they would performe great matters, and lead an Angels life: or if beeing here on earth they might ſee God come downe from heauen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they might haue ſome ſure token, that it was he that ſpake vnto them, as the Iſraelites had in the wildernes,<note place="margin">Exod. 19</note> when God ſpake there vnto them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mount Sinai, then they would yeeld great obedience, and nothing ſhould draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, which they had heard. Theſe and many ſuch foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and impoſſible things doe men deſire, &amp; then they ſay they would beleeue all things, and vntill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they neede not, neither will they.</p>
            <p>But what ſaith the Apoſtle to the Romanes?<note place="margin">Rom. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The righteouſnes which is of faith, ſpeaketh on this wiſe, Say not in thine heart, who ſhall aſcend into heauen? (that is, to bring Chriſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:14254:90"/> from aboue) or who ſhall deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deepe? (that is, to bring Chriſt from the dead.) But what ſaith it? The word is neere thee euen in thy mouth, and in thine heart; this is the word of faith which wee preach. Where he ſheweth what are the doubtfull and wauering thoughts of vnbeleeuers concerning that ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is purchaſed for vs by Chriſt, and offered vnto vs in the Goſpel: &amp; how thoſe thoughts &amp; imaginations by faith are to be repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed. For they which ſeek righteouſnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, that by the workes of the law they might be iuſtified and ſaued, beeing alwaies vnquiet and doubtfull of their ſaluation, becauſe they cannot finde perfect righteouſnes in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, are ready to ſay, if I might ſee any Saint or Angel come from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to cary me thither, or to aſſure me that I ſhall come thither; or any come from the depth of hell to tell
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:14254:90"/> me, that I am deliuered from thence, I could beleeue it.</p>
            <p>But the righteouſnes of faith, that is, true faith whereby we are made righteous in Chriſt, ſuppreſſeth theſe thoughts of vnbeleefe; and telleth vs according to that, that is preached in the Goſpel, that Chriſt hath fulfilled all things needefull for our ſaluation; euen that he hath ſuffered the curſe of the law to deliuer vs from hel, and that he hath fulfilled the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the law to bring vs to heauen, and he hath aſcended vp thither for vs in our nature, to prepare a place for vs: and he hath praied vnto God for vs, that where he is we may be to behold his glorie. Thus true faith for the certentie of our ſaluation, bids vs rely vpon that, that Chriſt hath don for vs, and vpon that, which this way is ſet downe in the Goſpel: and ſo our conſciences ſhall be quieted, and no man neede to aske theſe queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14254:91"/> who can aſcend vp into heauen, or bring vs from hell? ſeeing that the Goſpel teacheth that both theſe are done by Chriſt for all thoſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their calling by a true faith.</p>
            <p>But vnbeleefe neglecting this, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth that, that is vnreaſonable, and ſaith, Oh, but I ſee none that hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended vp to heauen, &amp; come downe againe to tell me, what is there done for me. Who ſhall aſcend? who is he that hath, or will doe ſo much? then I could beleeue it. And I ſee none, that hath deſcended into hell, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, to tell me that I am deliuered from thence. Who ſhall deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deepe? where is he that hath, or will doe this for me? then I could beleeue it. And ſo not onely the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers are wholly poſſeſſed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with theſe doubtfull thoughts; but all men, ſo farre as vnbeleefe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaileth in them, are ready to ſay thus, at leaſt in their hearts, Oh, if any
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14254:91"/> might come from heauen, to aſſure me, that I ſhall come thither, and be ſaued, then I could beleeue it: or if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny might come from hell, to aſſure me that I am deliuered from thence, then I ſhould be quiet in my minde, and deliuered from theſe feares, that I am incombred with.</p>
            <p>But what ſaith faith? ſay not thus in thine heart, &amp;c. that is, haue thou no ſuch doubts in thy mind, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what Chriſt hath done for thee, to bring thee to heauen, and to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee from hell: and what the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel doth this way offer vnto thee, and what thou haſt heard preached out of it to this ende, and reſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For if thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus,<note place="margin">Rom. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in thine heart that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: that is, if thou profeſſe plainely, and ſincerely, and openly, that thou takeſt Ieſus onely to be thy Lord and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:14254:92"/> Sauiour; and that it was the very counſell and purpoſe of God, in the reſurrection of his ſonne to redeeme vs from death, and hell, as it is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto vs in the Goſpel, thou ſhalt be ſaued. So faith leadeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe vain ſpeculations vnto that, that is reuealed vnto vs in the word.</p>
            <p>And whereas the beſt beleeuers are ſubiect vnto theſe temptations at one time or other, by reaſon of the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nants of vnbeleefe abiding in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet the Apoſtle giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that they come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnbeleefe, and not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith: but that it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſaith to ſtriue againſt them, &amp; to ſuppreſſe them in meaſure, ſo farre forth as faith preuaileth, and getteth the victory in them. So that when they begin to haue theſe doubts in their minds, and to thinke with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how ſhal I aſcend into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? how ſhall I eſcape hell, I cannot tell what ſhall become of me? then faith
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14254:92"/> is as a voice ſpeaking behind them, to admoniſh them of their duty, and as it were pulling them by the elbow bids them hold their peace, Oh ſay not in thine heart, who ſhall aſcend into heauen, &amp;c. Oh haue no ſuch thoughts in thy mind: this were to deny what Chriſt hath done for thee concerning thy redemption from hell, and thy aſcention into heauen: therefore ſay not ſo in any caſe, no not in thine heart: giue ouer reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with vnbeleefe, and reſt in the word of God.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how vnbeleefe bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth God to vnreaſonable courſes, &amp; deſireth of him for the ſtrengthening of faith things not to be deſired: therefore as we ſee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence ſuch do ariſe, ſo we muſt ſtriue againſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, that we might ouercome ſuch fooliſh conceits. And thus the vnbeleuing Iewes did reaſon againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, when he was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14254:93"/> the croſſe, and thereby did ſhew what wicked and abſurd thoughts their infidelitie did driue them vnto. If thou be the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Matth. 27.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> come downe from the croſſe: he ſaued o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but he cannot ſaue himſelfe: if he be the king of Iſrael,<note place="margin">42.</note> let him now come downe from the croſſe, and we will beleeue in him:<note place="margin">43.</note> he truſted in God, let him deliuer him now, if he will haue him: for he ſaide, I am the ſonne of God. Behold what vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable things they doe, as it were, binde Chriſt vnto, that they might beleeue in him, or els they will not: for they ſay, let him now come down from the croſſe, and now ſaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or els neuer.</p>
            <p>They did not conſider how all the propheſies of the Meſſiah ſet downe in Scripture were verified in him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from his firſt conception, vnto this very houre: how he was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14254:93"/> a virgin, and of the houſe of Dauid, and in Bethleem: how the wiſe men came from the Eaſt vnto Ieruſalem, and told them that the King of the Iewes was borne, and that they had ſeene his ſtarre: neither what old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Simeon, and Anna the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe ſaid of him in the temple, when he was circumciſed. They regarded not his doctrine ful of authoritie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, themſelues beeing driuen to confeſſe, that neuer man before ſpake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike vnto him: they were not moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with his miracles, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw how by his owne power he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed them of incurable diſeaſes, made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he blind to ſee, the lame to goe, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eafe to heare: caſt out the deuills by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he power of his word; raiſed vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat were dead: and did many more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings els, which were ſufficient to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onuince them, that he was the true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſiah and Sauiour, to whome all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Prophets gaue witneſſe: neither
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:14254:94"/> did they giue any credit vnto the voice of God himſelfe, which they heard from heauen, when he was baptized,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> This is my beloued ſonne, in whome I am well pleaſed: at what time alſo the heauens were opened, and the Spirit of God deſcended like a doue, and lighted vpon him. Much leſſe did they giue credit vnto the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Iohn, who ſaide of him, Behold the lambe of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.36.</note> that taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</p>
            <p>None of all theſe they regarded they were not ſufficient to cauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to beleeue in him, they deſpiſed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all, as though they had been nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worth; but ſuch a fooliſh thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this they deſire, and that ſhould ſatis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fie them: if he would come down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the croſſe, and that <hi>euen ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> now</hi> at their appointment, and tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> no longer, then they could beleeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him indeede: but if he would not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that at all, or not now preſently wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:14254:94"/> out any delay they will not beleeue in him. Which if he had done, he had forſaken his office of redemption, for he came to ſuffer and die for vs, that he might by his owne ſufferings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs from death, and to die vpon the croſſe,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> that he might redeeme vs from the curſe of the law, beeing made a curſe for vs, as it is written, Curſed is euery one that hangeth on tree. And when he had ſuffered all things needefull for our ſaluation, ſaying vpon the croſſe, It is finiſhed,<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.30.</note> and ſo gaue vp the ghoſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was buried: God raiſed him vp at the time appointed, euen the third day, and looſed the ſorowes of death,<note place="margin">Act. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> becauſe it was impoſſible, that hee ſhould be held of it any longer, as S. Peter ſaith. But ſee the fooliſhnes of vnbeleefe, the Iewes would haue god then to deliuer him before it was time, euen ſo ſoone as he was vpon the croſſe, and before he had ſuffered,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:14254:95"/> or els they would not beleeue that he was the ſonne of God, or that he had any power to ſaue himſelfe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>And after this manner the Deuill teacheth other men alſo by vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe to reaſon againſt good men, and againſt themſelues: as if ſuch a man were an vpright man, ſuch an one as he maketh ſhew of, God would not ſuffer him to be ſo and ſo afflicted, but he would deliuer him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this croſſe, that is vpon him: and ſo did the three friends of Iob reaſon againſt him to the great weakning of his faith: as this was alſo none of the leaſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations vnto Dauid, when the wicked ſaide of him in his miſerie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.10.</note> Where is now thy God? as if they had ſaide, Surely, if God were his God, he would haue deliuered him long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this. And of themſelues they are ready to ſay, if God would now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me out of this affliction; if hee
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:14254:95"/> would now helpe me out of this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I would thinke that he had ſome care of me indeede: and vnleſſe they haue ſome preſent eaſe, or releefe, they can not be perſwaded of the truth of his promiſes. But what ſaith the Scripture?<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> Call vpon me in the day of thy trouble: ſo will I deliuer thee. So that we muſt ſeek vnto God for the performance of his promiſes: But how? euen as it is ſaide in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalme,<note place="margin">&amp; 5.3.</note> Heare my voice in the morning, O Lord: for in the morning will I direct me vnto thee, and I will waite: that is, after that he had prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto God, he would patiently waite vpon him with truſt, till God did ſhew, that he had heard him. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as ſuiters doe at the court, when they haue put vp their petitions vnto the King, or the Counſell, though they haue not a preſent anſwer, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re not diſcouraged, and therefore giue ſtill attendance, and tarie their
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:14254:96"/> leiſure, with hope of ſpeeding at the laſt.</p>
            <p>And how long muſt we thus wait vpon God for his deliuerance? euen vntill it pleaſeth him to diſcharge vs: not preſcribing vnto him any time. Euen as it is ſaid in one of the Pſalms of degres,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. 130.6.</note> My ſoule waiteth on the Lord, more then the morning watch watcheth for the morning: that is, euen as they that are ſet to watch all night, doe not giue ouer their ſtation till the morning come, though the night be neuer ſo long: ſo we in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction muſt not ceaſe waiting vpon God vntill the time appointed. And when is that? euen when he giueth vs our hearts deſire, &amp; not before. Euen as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh in the name &amp; perſon of the whole church, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after what manner, and how long he would ſeeke vnto God.<note place="margin">&amp; 123.2.</note> Behold, as the eies of ſeruants looke vnto the hand of their maſters, and as the eies
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14254:96"/> of a maide vnto the hand of her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris; ſo our eies wait vpon the Lord our God, vntill he haue mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. So that he would continually and earneſtly wait vpon God for his defence, not doubting of it, vntill ſuch time as he found it by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and therefore if he deferre a while, we muſt tarie the longer, with good hope waiting. As the Prophet Habacuk ſaith, that after long prayer hee receiued this anſwer from the Lord concerning the deliuerance of the Church: that it was deferred a long time, therefore he would haue him to waite, for vndoubtedly in time it ſhould come, and not faile, ſaying,<note place="margin">Habak. 2.3.</note> The viſion is yet for an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, but at the laſt it ſhall ſpeake, and not lie: though it tary, yet wait thou, for it ſhall ſurely come, and ſhall not ſtay.</p>
            <p>But vnbeleefe ſaith, I could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeue theſe promiſes, if I might now
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:14254:97"/> inioy them, and vnles I be preſently deliuered, I cannot thinke, that God regardeth me: and ſo it tieth Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to preſent deliuerance. And though the Scripture hath ſaid, that affliction is like vnto fire, and that our faith and patience is like vnto gold; and therefore as the gold muſt tarie in the fire vntill all the droſſe be conſumed, and the gold refined: ſo God wil haue vs to indure the croſſe, vntill our corruption be thoroughly purged, and our faith and patience b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prooued to be pure and good; yet we are readie to ſay, that vnleſſe he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me now, I cannot beleeue, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he hath any reſpect vnto me. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto all that, which faith ſaith vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, concerning the tarying of God leiſure; vnbeleefe is readie to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwer, that vnleſſe God giue it now I will thinke that I ſhall neuer haue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And as faith or vnbeleefe preuailet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in vs at any time; ſo are theſe thogh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:14254:97"/> more or leſſe in vs, in the time of any affliction: for the one is of the fleſh, and the other of the Spirit, and both theſe beeing in the regenerate,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17</note> The fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, &amp; the Spirit againſt the fleſh; and theſe are contrarie one to an other: ſo that ye can not doe the ſame things that ye would, as Paul ſheweth to the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</p>
            <p>And this is that, which euery one of vs hath experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of in our ſelues: for how often when we haue beene in trouble, haue we thought, and ſaid in our owne hearts; vnles God giue me ſuch and ſuch meanes, there are none that will doe me good: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe theſe helpe me, I can not looke for helpe from any: and ſo we are readie to tie Gods helpe to times, and to meanes. Whereas faith ſaith otherwiſe out of the word of God, namely, that he hath other times, and meanes in his hands to doe vs good
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:14254:98"/> by, and that he is able to helpe vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all meanes faile vs. And beſides, what if he will not deliuer vs at all? but wil haue vs drinke of that cuppe, that he hath giuen vs, euen vnto death: as Chriſt himſelfe did: his loue is neuer a whit the leſſe vnto vs, no more then it was vnto him. Thus we ſee, how this vnbeleefe raigneth in this world, and yet how Chriſt of his infinite goodneſſe and mercie, beareth with thoſe that are his in it for a while, and cureth them of it at the laſt, as he did with the Apoſtle <hi>Thomas,</hi> and as he hath done with vs very often, and in many things.</p>
            <p>And this is that, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet noteth to haue beene very often in the people of Iſrael, whiles they were in the wildernes, of whome he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 78.41</note> They returned, and tempted God, and limited the holy one of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: that is, according to the ſtraitnes of their owne heart in their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14254:98"/> ſo did they imagine of Gods preſence and power: and therefore they are ſaid, to limit the holy one of Iſrael, and as it were to compaſſe him in certaine bounds, and to indent with him after this manner: if hee would doe ſo and ſo for them, they would thinke that he cared for them, and were among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their good: &amp; if he would not doe ſo, they would not beleeue it. And thus they did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and therefore it is ſaide, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and tempted God: for when they had te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted God thus one way, then they did it an other way. For ſometimes they deſired water, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meate, ſometimes daintie fleſh, as quailes; and that ſo importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they ſaid, vnles they had theſe things according to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, they thought either that God could not doe it, or that he cared not for them: and thus they ſpake againſt God, ſaying,<note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> Can God prepare a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14254:99"/> in the wildernes? behold, he ſmote the rocke that the waters guſhed out, and the ſtreames ouerflowed: can he giue bread alſo, and prepare fleſh for his people? And thus did they not onely once, but many times, and for many things: in ſo much that the Prophet ſpeaketh with admiration, How oft did they prouoke him in the wilderneſſe, and grieue him in the deſert! And thus for their aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that God was with them, and that he was willing and able to helpe them, they deſired theſe outward things, &amp; ſo by the fooliſhnes of their deſires did apparantly ſhew the vnbeleefe that was in them.</p>
            <p>So doe many vnbeleeuers of our time: looke what they earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, if they haue it not, they will not beleeue that God careth for them: &amp; hereupon ſome of them ſay, if I might haue ſuch a thing, I would think that God loued me: and others
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:14254:99"/> ſay, if God would beſtowe this or that vpon me, I would hope that I were in his fauour. And what things are they then which they deſire? one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly outward, and appertaining to this life: and ſo according to their preſent wants through vnbeleefe they limite the loue of God, ſome to one thing, ſome to an other, and will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of it, but by the inioying of ſuch things as themſelues deſire.</p>
            <p>And it is thus not onely in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers: but all Gods children, ſo farre as the remnants of vnbeleefe do preuaile in them, are ſubiect vnto theſe temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and to theſe deſires: and are ready to ſay, if I were rid of this affliction, which hath lien hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily vpon me a long time, I could be perſwaded of his fauour towards me. By which we are thus to profit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſee, what infidelity is lurking in vs, that ſo we might be ſory for it, &amp; ſeeke to be holpen of it. And then we
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14254:100"/> ſhall ſee the remedie againſt it to be this: that as the Apoſtle S. Thomas ſhould not haue tied the certenty of Chriſts reſurrection, to his appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſhewing of himſelfe vnto him, ſaying, Vnles I ſee him my ſelfe, I will not beleeue it: for it was true, &amp; to be beleeued of him and others, that Chriſt was riſen againe, though they had neuer ſeene him: much leſſe ſhould he haue tied it vnto this, that he would ſee him in that forme, that he was in vpon the croſſe, with the wounds and marks in his bodie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Vnles I ſee in his hands the print of the nayles, and put my finger into the print of the nayles, and put my hand into his ſide, I will not beleeue it: for he might haue appeared vnto him in ſome other forme, as he did vnto others, at diuers times.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo we are not to tie the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentie of Gods fauour to any one thing, and to ſay, vnles I haue this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:14254:100"/> that, I can not be perſwaded of Gods fauour: much leſſe vnto any of theſe outward things, which appertaine vnto our bodies, and to this life: for God our heauenly father hath many waies and meanes to aſſure his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of his loue and fauour towards them; and doth it as our earthly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe, not onely to ſome one way, and to others an other way, but euen vnto the ſame not alike at all times, and by the ſame things. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially there are more ſure pledges and tokens of his loue, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon his children, then all the outward benefits in the world; which onely for the moſt part the vnbeleeuers deſire, and meaſure gods fauour by them. For there are the graces &amp; gifts of his holy Spirit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vnto the elect, as a loue of God and of goodnes, an hatred of euill, a deſire to pleaſe God, a delight in the companie of the godly, and ſuch like:
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14254:101"/> in beſtowing of which vpon man, he doth moſt of all manifeſt his loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. There are alſo his holy word and Sacraments, whereby he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the beginning and increaſe of theſe and other graces in thoſe that are his: rare and ineſtimable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of his fauour: of which it is ſaid in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>al. 147.19.</note> He ſheweth his word vnto Iaakob, his ſtatutes &amp; his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vnto Iſrael: he hath not dealt ſo with euery nation, neither haue they known his iudgements. Where he maketh this a note of the loue of God to the people of the Iewes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other nations, that they had among them the doctrine of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, which others wanted. And ſo this is none of the leaſt teſtimonies of Gods fauour towardes vs, that we liue in theſe happie daies and bleſſed times, in which the Goſpel is purely and ſincerely preached, and that we inioy the miniſterie of it.</p>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:14254:101"/>
            <p>But the greateſt token of all, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God hath manifeſted his loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vs, is the death of his ſonne: of which Chriſt ſpeaketh in the goſpel, God ſo loued the world,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.16.</note> that he gaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is onely begotten ſonne, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oeuer beleeueth in him, ſhould not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eriſh, but haue euerlaſting life: wher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e noteth the excellency of the loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God, by the excellency of the gift. He ſo loued the world with an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdinarie and wonderfull great loue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he gaue his onely begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſaue vs: and this is the fountaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cauſe of all other benefits of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtowed, and to be beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the Apoſtle ſaith;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.32.</note> God that ſpared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot his owne ſonne, but gaue him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r vs all to death, how ſhall he not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith him giue vs all things alſo? and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him there are purchaſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red for vs euerlaſting ioyes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngdome of heauen: and though we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ant many things in this world, yet
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14254:102"/> God giueth vs patience, and mindes well contented with our eſtate, as a token that he loueth vs. So that by all theſe things, or by any one of them, and by many more is Gods loue knowen and to be beleeued. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we muſt not be ſo fooliſh to ſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God by vnbeleefe, and ſay, if I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue this or that, I will be perſwade of his fauour: for there are othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things beſides thoſe which we im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gine, whereby he may manifeſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fauour vnto vs moſt clearly: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo not onely in this world, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the world to come: not onely whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we haue in preſent poſſeſſion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which we inioy through hope.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is ſingula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commended in the faith of Iob, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had loſt al his worldly goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in reſpect of his outward eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he was brought vnto nothing; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did put his truſt in God: beleeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that his fauour was not tied to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:14254:102"/> nor to any one of them: but that it was the ſame then, that it was before: and ſo vttered this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable ſpeach proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith in Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;<note place="margin">Iob 1.21.</note> Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne thither: the Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken it, bleſſed be the name of the Lord. He doth not ſay, if God would reſtore all vnto me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (as he did in time, yea he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed them) then I would beleeue that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e cared for me: but euen whiles he remained in the want of all, he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and praiſed the name of God; which could not be without great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith. Yea he ſaid further, that if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould die in that eſtate, yet he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at his truſt in God, and beleeue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at he cared for him:<note place="margin">&amp; 13 15</note> Loe though he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay me, yet will I truſt in him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſhall be my ſaluation: in which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ords he confeſſeth, that he was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, euen in this great extremitie,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14254:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:14254:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="196" facs="tcp:14254:104"/> from deſpairing of life or ſaluation, as that in the very power and inſtant of death he would truſt in him; for he had other teſtimonies of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, then all his outward proſperity: euen the teſtimony of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that he had walked before him in ſincerity and truth, and that he had been no hypocrite; as he declareth at large in the Chap. 31.</p>
            <p>And he had further, for the vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his faith, the conſtant truth of Gods promiſes; and thoſe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this life, but for the life to come: and therefore he doubted not, but that it ſhould goe well with him, though he died in that eſtate: for he hoped at the laſt day to riſe againe, &amp; to behold Chriſt his Sauiour to his euerlaſting comfort: when he ſaith, Oh that my words were now writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">and 19.23.</note> oh that they were written euen in a booke: and grauen with an iron pen, in lead or in ſtone for euer; for I am
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:14254:104"/> ſure that my redemer liueth, and he ſhall ſtand the laſt on the earth: and though after my skinne wormes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this body, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh, whom I ſhall ſee my ſelfe, and my eies ſhall behold, and none other for me, though my reines are conſumed within me. Where we ſee how he ſaith, that in the midſt of all his afflictions he did reioyce and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in this, euen in the teſtimony of a good conſcience, whereby he did ſo reſt in the promiſes of God concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his reſurrection, and life eternal, which was to come, that this did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme him in the fauour of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all temptations.</p>
            <p>Thus true faith bindeth not Gods fauor to any of theſe outward things, whereby men doe commonly deſire to be aſſured of it: but it looketh vnto better things, whereby his loue is moſt apparant; and that not onely in this life, but in the life to come moſt
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:14254:105"/> of all: as they be promiſed and ſet downe in the word of God. And that is the remedie againſt the fooliſh &amp; vaine deſires of vnbeleefe. Let vs not therefore tie the aſſurance of Gods fauour vnto any one thing, but ſeeing that he hath many waies to declare it, let vs beleeue the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his word, and pray him to ſeale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in our hearts by what meanes it ſhall pleaſe him beſt: and let vs not be ſo froward and peruerſe, as to thinke it is not conſtant vnto vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it be ſealed vp that way, which we our ſelues doe moſt of all deſire.</p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude the ſumme of all in few words. We ſee by the weakenes of S. Thomas, not onely what we are ſubiect vnto, but alſo how we may helpe our ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt the ſame. He did not beleeue that Chriſt was riſen againe, though it was told him at ſundrie times by diuers, that were very cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible:
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:14254:105"/> we muſt therefore in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of faith giue credit vnto the word of God brought vnto vs, in the mouthes of his faithfull ſeruants, if they be but two or three. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in this caſe would beleeue none but himſelfe: we muſt beleeue in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of our ſaluation others rather then our ſelues, and thinke eſpecially that in the time of temptation others are able better to iudge of our eſtate, then we our ſelues can, and ſo be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo much addicted to our owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erweening.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he would beleeue nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this matter any further then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was able to ſee and feele: now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecauſe theſe may deceiue vs, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt beleeue without any ſight or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeling: eſpecially ſeeing that faith is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f things that are not ſeene, &amp; the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our of God is not alwaies ſenſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his benefits, we muſt beleeue his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord without: yea contrary to any
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:14254:106"/> thing, that we can ſee or feele. Laſtly, he would not beleeue except he ſaw Chriſt with his wounds, and ſo in that forme, which ordinarily was not to be looked for: we therefore muſt not by vnbeleefe tie the teſtimonies of Gods fauour for the aſſurance of our faith vnto ſuch things as are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and commonly not to be looked for: neither vnto any one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thing, becauſe he hath many waies to confirme the ſame vnto vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and pray him to giue vs grace, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we may profit in faith by any, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall beſtowe vpon vs.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is ſo hard a thing to beleeue, &amp; there is ſo much infide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie hidden in the hearts of the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God; let vs labour to ſearch into the depth of our owne, that fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding the ſame in our ſelues, we ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whiles we haue time vſe in feare a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thoſe good meanes, that God hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appointed for the beginning and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:14254:106"/> of faith in vs, that ſo by his bleſſing we daily going on forward from faith to faith, we may at the laſt come to that meaſure of it, againſt which the very gates of hell be not able to preuaile: that ſo we may both in temptation, and vnder all croſſes, and in the howre of death, ſo carrie our ſelues, as God may be glorified, we our ſelues may be comforted, and others may be furthered by our Chriſtian calling, and good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: which Chriſt the author and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith grant vnto vs, for his owne name ſake: to whome with the father and the holy Spirit, one true, immortall, inuiſible, and onely wiſe God, be aſcribed as moſt due all honour, praiſe, and glory for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
